<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The secrets and wonders of the world A booke right rare and straunge, containing many excellent properties, giuen to man, beastes, foules, fishes and serpents, trees, plants &amp;c. Abstracted out of that excellent naturall historiographer Plinie. Translated out of French into English.</title>
            <title>Naturalis historia. English. Abridgments</title>
            <author>Pliny, the Elder.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1585</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 121 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 32 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A09766</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 20032</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S110483</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99846020</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99846020</idno>
            <idno type="VID">10956</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A09766)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 10956)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 349:05)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The secrets and wonders of the world A booke right rare and straunge, containing many excellent properties, giuen to man, beastes, foules, fishes and serpents, trees, plants &amp;c. Abstracted out of that excellent naturall historiographer Plinie. Translated out of French into English.</title>
                  <title>Naturalis historia. English. Abridgments</title>
                  <author>Pliny, the Elder.</author>
                  <author>Alday, John, attributed name.</author>
                  <author>I. A.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[64] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed [by Henry Denham] for Thomas Hacket, are are to be solde at his shop in Lumberd streete, vnder the Popes head,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1585.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A translation of Pierre de Changy's French abstract of Pliny's "Naturalis historia". A previous edition (STC 20031) had translator's initials I.A., i.e. John Alday?.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A²  B-H⁴ I² .</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: Secrets and wonders of the worlde.</note>
                  <note>The last leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of a photostat of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Natural history --  Pre-Linnean works.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:10956:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:10956:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>THE</hi> Secrets and <hi>wonders of the world.</hi> A BOOKE RIGHT rare and ſtraunge, containing many excellent properties, giuen to Man, Beaſtes, Foules, Fiſhes and Serpents, Trees, Plants &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Abſtracted out of that</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent naturall Hiſtoriographer Plinie. Tranſlated out of French into Engliſh.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>At London</hi> 
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> Printed for <hi>Thomas Hacket, and are</hi> to be ſolde at his ſhop in Lum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berd ſtreete, vnder the Popes head. 1585.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:10956:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:10956:2"/>
            <head>To the vvorſhipful <hi>and his very good friend Maiſter</hi> Richard Candler, as one that wiſheth the fauour of God long &amp; happy life, encreaſe of worſhip, with continuall health and felicitie.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>O it is worſhipfull Syr, I haue deuiſed with my ſelfe many times howe to gratifie you with ſome token of my good will towardes you, but welth and abilitie lacking to accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſh my deſired pretence, yet nowe at the laſt, I haue preſumed knowing your wonted curteſies towardes all men, to dedicate this Abſtract of Plinies deſiring you to take it with as good a will as I haue ment it, till hereafter that ſome ſeriuſſer matter come to my hande, and thus I bid you moſt hartely farewell in the Lord, who keepe you and all yours, proſper and preſerue you in all your good and godly enterpriſes. Amen.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Yours to vſe. T. H.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:10956:3"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Ere haſt thou gentle Reader, ſet forth vnto thee this Booke, named <hi>The Secrets and wonders of the Worlde,</hi> abſtracted out of the ſixteene firſt Bookes of that excellent naturall Historio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grapher <hi>Plinie,</hi> for the ſtraungeneſſe and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thineſſe thereof, I referre thee to thine owne iudgement, requeſting thee to take this in good part, &amp; ſhortly ſhalbe by Gods grace, ſet forth vnto thee three worthy and learned bookes, the firſt is of the Cituation of the world, writte by <hi>Pomponius Mela,</hi> The ſecond is a perfite Pere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grination and true diſcouerie of <hi>Graecie, Turkey, Arabia,</hi> and <hi>Siria,</hi> with the maner of their Cities, and their Antiquities: The third is, <hi>Iulius Sol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linus Pollihiſtorie,</hi> the which bookes thou ſhalt finde both to be pleaſant and profitable, And thus I bid thee farewel in Chriſt, who keep vs. Ame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:10956:3"/>
            <head>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> The Secretes and <hi>wonders of the World, abſtracted</hi> out of the principall of the naturall Hiſtoriographers.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">P</seg>LINIE</hi> the naturall Hiſtoriographer, was borne vnder the Emperour <hi>Tyberian,</hi> and died vnder <hi>Titus,</hi> the Emperour that deſtroyed Hieruſalem, after the death and paſſion of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, in which time he did attribute his woorkes. In the firſt booke (which is briefe,) he maketh his preambles. In the ſecond, he treateth of the worlde, and of other matters.</p>
            <p>He deſcribeth that the worlde is alone and round, natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally vnmoueable, although that there are certaine places moueable, and that may moue, by the concauites of the earth, being full of winde.</p>
            <p>There are foure Elementes, the Earth, the Water, and the Fyre aboue the Ayre, néere to the firſt firmament. Which is fire natural, and therefore there néedeth no wood to continue the ſame.</p>
            <p>Vnder the Earth are the Planetes, which are called Strayers, and yet they moue leſſe then the others, but it is of the mutation of their influences, &amp; of the Firmament: among the which is the Sunne rector and the guider of the other Planets, principall gouernour of nature.</p>
            <p>The other Starres are not attributed (as ſome doe thinke, as the greateſt and cleareſt to the rich: and the leaſt to the poore, and the obſcure and darke ſtarres, to thoſe that
<pb facs="tcp:10956:4"/>of nature are infected. For we haue no ſuch ſocietie with the Starres, that they ſhoulde die with vs, and therefore they are equally deuided, ſeruing to eche one.</p>
            <p>The Moone hath her Planet comming before her, as the Sunne hath the day Starre, ſhe doeth encreaſe and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſh, and ſometimes is at the full, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d ſometimes ſhée hath hornes, euen as the Sunne doeth giue and take away her cleareneſſe.</p>
            <p>The earth is betwéene them both, the Moone is in the firſt heauen, the Sunne in the fourth, and when the one is highe, the other is lowe, and the other Starres are more higher in the Skie, and therefore they ſéeme leſſe then the Moone. The obſcuritie and darckeneſſe of the Moone, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth by the humours of the earth that is drawen or ſucked vp from the earth.</p>
            <p>By the <hi>Geometrie</hi> of this worlde, the Stade which is fourtie roddes, doeth containe <hi>125.</hi> paces, the whiche are <hi>525.</hi> foote. Sometimes there hath bene ſéene in the appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, thrée Sunnes, and thrée Moones.</p>
            <p>In the Aire it raineth ſometimes naturally Stones, ſuckt vp by the vapours of the earth, ſometimes Frogges, and ſome time blood in diuers figures.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Heliotropium</hi> in his floure, doeth turne euery day and followe the Sunne.</p>
            <p>The Ant doeth neuer beginne to hourde vp but in the full Moone.</p>
            <p>The nature of the windes are diuers, according to the diuerſitie of Countreies, and they procéed of the earth, and of the vapours of the ſame, which cauſeth ſometimes in many places Earthquakes.</p>
            <p>The Thunders and Lightnings, doe neuer fall in the winter, for the coldneſſe of the ayre doth kéepe them in and choakes them, and therefore they fall in the Sommer, and many times they marre the Wine, without touching the veſſell.</p>
            <p>There was a woman at <hi>Rome,</hi> whoſe childe was ſlaine
<pb facs="tcp:10956:4"/>within her wombe, by thunder and lightning, and the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man had no hurt at all.</p>
            <p>Thrée things there are that neuer féele any harme by thunders and lightnings: the <hi>Laurel</hi> trée on the Earth, the <hi>Eagle</hi> in the Skie, and the <hi>Seacalſe</hi> in the Sea, for they ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer fall vpon their ſkinnes, therefore beſt aſſured are they that are ſo clad.</p>
            <p>Naturally there are ſignes and tokens in the earth, the Sea, and the Aire, and therefore it hath rained ſometimes Blood, Stones, Wooll, yea great ſtones accumulated in the ayre by the coldneſſe thereof.</p>
            <p>The Rainebowe is not ſéene in a cloſe and rainy day, but the Sunne beames entring into the concauites of the Earth, doe reflexe the Sunne, and make varietie of co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours, by the mixture of the cloudes in the aire, and is ſéene moſt commonly in the Sommer. Alſo there are neuer lightly ſéene aboue two Rainbowes.</p>
            <p>The earth is the mother of all liuing creatures. In the aire is ſéene many times darkeneſſe &amp; clowdes, the Hailes are deriued of the waters, but the earth is lowly, ſeruing to all creatures, ſhe bringeth forth Corne, Wine, Fruites, and all kinde of things pertaining to man. Shée bringeth foorth Iron, Lead, Golde, Siluer, precious Stones, and Herbes, ſeruing vnto mans health, yea, if that a Serpent chaunce to bite any perſon, the earth will not receiue that Serpent when it is dead.</p>
            <p>The earth is compaſſed round about with waters, the which is more knowen by experience, then by arguments, and ſome part thereof is not inhabited towards the North, becauſe of the great colde.</p>
            <p>An other part is not inhabited becauſe of the extreame heate, towards the South.</p>
            <p>The middle of the earth is the Centry, to the which moſt waightieſt things doe take holde.</p>
            <p>In ſome places there is no ſhadowe of the Sunne, ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially in <hi>Alexandria</hi> the great, where as there is a déepe
<pb facs="tcp:10956:5"/>well without ſhadowe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anaxemenes Mileſius,</hi> was the firſt founders of Dials.</p>
            <p>There are many ſignes of mouings, and mutations of times, without great appearance, as in the Sea, when that without winde, the waues doe riſe and rage. And in the Skie, when that there is a long ſtripe or line: and when that the well waters are troubled.</p>
            <p>Two mountaines haue bene ſéene naturally hit and touch one another, as if they had foughten, the waters méeting together to ſtriue and marueilouſly to encreaſe, and beaſtes to dye.</p>
            <p>In <hi>Aſia</hi> twelue Cities were ſubuerted by the Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quakes, without perceiuing thereof at <hi>Rome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Neare vnto <hi>Rome</hi> there are two hundreth acres of ground, the which doeth ſhake when there are horſes run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning thereon.</p>
            <p>In the Ile of <hi>Paphos</hi> there is a place where there did neuer fall rayne. And in the ſame Ile <hi>Nea</hi> in the Citie of <hi>Troados,</hi> the ſacrifices do neuer putrifie nor rot.</p>
            <p>Nere to <hi>Harpaſa</hi> a towne in <hi>Aſia,</hi> there is a great Mou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, that one may ſhake with their finger, but if you put your whole ſtrength to it, it remaineth vnmoueable.</p>
            <p>There are two Mountaines neare to the flood of <hi>Nyle,</hi> the nature of them are diuers, for the one retaineth yron, the other caſteth it off, in ſuch ſort, that if any of their ſhooes be clouted with nailes, that goe vpon the ſaid hill, they can neither go nor ſtande, but are caſt off: and on the other hil, their ſhoes will ſticke faſt.</p>
            <p>In the Citie of <hi>Charagena,</hi> there is a certaine grounde that healeth all kinde of ſores and diſeaſes, the Sea doeth purge in the full Moone: and the fluctuations of the Seas, commeth by the Sunne and Moone, the which cauſeth it. In the hie Sea there neuer falleth ſnowe, the Sea is moſt hotteſt in Winter, and ſalteſt in Sommer. Of freſh wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters there are diuers ſortes.</p>
            <p>In <hi>Dodone</hi> is the Frountaine called <hi>Iupiters Spring,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:10956:5"/>which doeth kindle firebrandes, it diminiſheth at Noone, and encreaſeth at midnight, and then afterwards decrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth, and faileth at midday. There are many hote waters, becauſe of the ſmoke &amp; cloſeneſſe of the hilles, from whence theſe hote waters ſpring.</p>
            <p>There are Springs that will make blacke Shéepe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come white, and other waters that maketh white ſhéepe become blacke, by continuance of drinking, and others that the ewes that drinke in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their milke will become black.</p>
            <p>At <hi>Linceſtis,</hi> there is a Fountaine of water, that will make them that drinke thereof drunken.</p>
            <p>Alſo in <hi>Paphlagonia,</hi> and in the field <hi>Calenus,</hi> in the Ile of <hi>Andro,</hi> there is a Fountaine or Spring, that rendreth wine euery yéere in the <hi>Nonas</hi> of Ianuarie.</p>
            <p>In a fielde called <hi>Carrimenſis,</hi> in <hi>Spaine,</hi> there is a Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer that will make the fiſhes that are therin, to ſéeme of the colour of golde, and if they are put into any other water, they will ſéeme as other fiſhes.</p>
            <p>Among the meruailes of fire, the Mountaine called <hi>Ethna,</hi> in <hi>Silicia,</hi> burneth continually, the flames whereof are ſéene aboue the hill toppe. An other hill that is called <hi>Chimera,</hi> burneth in like maner, the fire of which hill is ſooner quenched with earth or with hay, then with water.</p>
            <p>In the third, fourth, fifth, and ſixth bookes, <hi>Plinie</hi> deſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth the earth, the waters and the Ilandes, and deuideth the worlde into <hi>Aſia, Affrica,</hi> and <hi>Europa. Aſia</hi> conteineth the halfe of the world, in the which is <hi>Armenia, Capadocia, Albania, Suauia,</hi> where as there is no mettall but gold. <hi>Sei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thies,</hi> where as is the ſwéete Sea, and there are trees that bring forth ſilke, ready to ſpinne.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>India,</hi> where there are people very riche, they labour with Elephantes, and go to warre with them. Their king hath ordinarily ſixe hundreth thouſand footemen, thirtie thouſand horſemen, &amp; nine thouſand Camels to his gages, and to his daily coſt, and when they be ſo olde that they can ſcarſe ſee, nor can liue no longer, they caſt them ſelues into
<pb facs="tcp:10956:6"/>a great fire.</p>
            <p>Beyonde the <hi>Indians,</hi> is the Ile called <hi>Taprobane,</hi> where as is the gréene Sea, and there is planted precious ſtones, with mettalls of gold and ſiluer.</p>
            <p>The men of that Countrey are more greater then o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, they ſell their marchandiſe by making of ſignes, the Moone neuer ſhineth with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> aboue ſixe houres, they haue ſmall edifices or buildings, &amp; their vitailes neuer waxeth deare: for their God they haue <hi>Hercules.</hi> They doe elect and chooſe an olde man to their King, which hath no chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, and if he chaunce to haue any whileſt he is king, they doe kill them, to that ende that the kingdome be not inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rited by their elected king: they doe conſtitute. xxx. gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours, without whoſe aſſent none can bee condemned to death. If their king doeth miſdoe, they doe puniſh him, or depoſe him from the crowne.</p>
            <p>This nation taketh great delite in the chaſe of Tigres and Clephantes, and doeth abounde in corne and fruites, they doe delight to fiſhe for ſhell fiſhes, which are there very great, in ſo much that one may hide themſelues in their ſhelles.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Alexandria</hi> the great was founded by the great king <hi>Alexander,</hi> and neare vnto that is the redde Sea, by the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>percuſſion of the Sunne, that doeth ſo colour it, or els for that the mood and the grauell is ſuch, or for that it is the nature of the water.</p>
            <p>Alſo <hi>Siria</hi> and <hi>Arabia,</hi> whoſe people are ta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ned and heary all ſaue the head, and they are apparelled with the ſkinnes of fiſh.</p>
            <p>There is alſo <hi>Meſopotanie, Babylon, Aſſiria, Arabia:</hi> the flood of <hi>Tyger,</hi> hath his originall in a fountaine of <hi>Arme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the Ile of <hi>Sagaros,</hi> there can no Dogge liue, for as ſoone as he entereth into the Ile, he turneth round till hée fall downe dead.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Sabiens</hi> are riche with the fertilitie of their For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſts,
<pb facs="tcp:10956:6"/>with mettals, Hony, and Waxe.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Candeans</hi> liue with Serpentes, and in the Ile of <hi>Gagaudes</hi> was firſt founde Popeniayes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Idumea, Iuda, Hieruſalem, Galile, Sirie, Paleſtin,</hi> which was the firſt founder of letters, and at the firſt, in ſtéede of letters, vſed certaine figures of beaſtes.</p>
            <p>Alſo there is a Nation called <hi>Heſſeneans,</hi> liuing with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out wyues, and without lecherie. When they are dead, they are caſt into the Sea, they liue without money, and growe of the dead.</p>
            <p>Of the <hi>Ethiopians</hi> there are diuers formes and kindes of men. Some there are towards the Eaſt, that haue nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther noſe nor noſtrelles, but the face all full. Others that haue no vpper lippe, they are without tongues, and they ſpeake by ſignes, and they haue but a little hole to take their breath at, by the which they drinke with an Oten ſtrawe.</p>
            <p>There are ſome called <hi>Syrbote,</hi> that are eight foote high, they liue with the chaſe of Elephantes.</p>
            <p>In a part of <hi>Affricke,</hi> by people called <hi>Ptoemphane,</hi> for their king they haue a Dogge, at whoſe fanſie they are go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerned, to whome they doe pronoſticate their doings, and their conduct in warre.</p>
            <p>Towards the Weſt there is a people called <hi>Arimaſpi,</hi> that hath but one eye in their forehead, they are in the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſert and wilde Countrey.</p>
            <p>The people called <hi>Agriphagi,</hi> liue with the fleſh of Pa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers and Lyons: and the people called <hi>Antropomphagi</hi> which we call <hi>Canibals,</hi> liue with humaine fleſh.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Cinamolgi,</hi> their heades are almoſte like to the heads of Dogges.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Affrica</hi> aunciently called <hi>Libia,</hi> doeth containe the <hi>Moores,</hi> and the pillers of <hi>Hercules,</hi> (among the ſloods) there is <hi>Onylus</hi> that doeth ingender Cocodrils.</p>
            <p>There are goodly Forreſts with vnknowen trées, ſome of the which trees beare ſmall threades, of the which is
<pb facs="tcp:10956:7"/>made clothing of Cotton.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Cyrenes</hi> and <hi>Syrtes,</hi> make their houſes of ſalt ſtones, cut out of the mountaines, there is the mountaine of <hi>Giry,</hi> the which doeth ingender and bring foorth many precious ſtones.</p>
            <p>In <hi>Libie,</hi> which is at the ende of the <hi>Ethiopes,</hi> there are people, differing from the common order of others, they haue among them no names, and they curſe the Sunne for his great heate, by the which they are all blacke ſauing their téeth, and a little the palme of their handes, and they neuer dreame. The others called <hi>Troglodites,</hi> haue Caues and holes in the grounde, and haue no other houſes. O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers called <hi>Gramantes,</hi> they make no marriages, but all women are common. <hi>Gamphaſantes,</hi> they goe all naked.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Blemmy</hi> is a people ſo called, they haue no heads, but haue their mouth and their eyes in their breaſts. And o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers there are that go more by training of their handes then with their féete. There are gathered the ſpices, and there is nothing that they are afrayde of, but of great dogs that will barke at them, and bite them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Africke</hi> beginneth beyonde the Realme of <hi>Spayne</hi> and <hi>Grenado,</hi> and is deuided in the Sea of <hi>Europa,</hi> as betwéene <hi>Douer</hi> and <hi>Calis,</hi> there beginneth the Kingdoms of <hi>Feoz,</hi> of <hi>Tunis,</hi> of <hi>Barbaria,</hi> of <hi>Carthage,</hi> &amp; of others of the <hi>Ethiopians.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Europia</hi> beginneth from the Sea <hi>Meditarene</hi> ſo called, becauſe it is a flood in the middeſt of the world. Vpon this Sea that deuideth <hi>Aſia</hi> and <hi>Europa,</hi> the King <hi>Xerſes</hi> cauſed to be made a bridge of ſhippes, ſuch a number hee had for the warre.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Europa</hi> conteineth <hi>Rome</hi> the auncient Citie, the plenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full <hi>Italy, Venice</hi> deſcended of the <hi>Troyans, Grece, Theſſalia, Acaia, Macedonia,</hi> and <hi>Theſſalie,</hi> where as is a flood called <hi>Peneus,</hi> nauigable in the middeſt, for into the ſaide flood en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treth the Riuer of <hi>Orcon,</hi> but his water ſwimmeth aboue the other, without mingling together as doeth Oyle. <hi>Italy</hi> hath the noble Riuer of <hi>Poſte,</hi> beating vaines of golde.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:10956:7"/>
            <p>In the Iles of <hi>Pont,</hi> there are people that liue with the egges of wilde foule, others that haue féete like horſes, whoſe eares are ſo great and ſo long, that therewith they couer their whole bodies.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Europe</hi> doeth containe <hi>Germanie,</hi> which is hie and baſe <hi>Almaine, Burgony, Sauoy, Brittaine, Gaule</hi> that is deuided into thrée partes.</p>
            <p>From the Riuer <hi>Leſcault</hi> to the Riuer of <hi>Sayne</hi> is called <hi>Gaule</hi> the faire, from <hi>Sayne,</hi> to <hi>Gyrrond,</hi> is <hi>Gaule</hi> the ancie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, and conteineth <hi>Lionois,</hi> and from <hi>Girronde</hi> to the hilles of <hi>Pirennes,</hi> that deuideth <hi>Spaine</hi> and <hi>Fraunce,</hi> is <hi>Aquittaine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Spaine</hi> alſo is of <hi>Europia</hi> where as is <hi>Cathelognia, Arara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gon, Caſtilian, Portingall, Syuell, Andeloſia, Leon, Galicia,</hi> and the kingdome of <hi>Granado,</hi> euen to the Sea.</p>
            <div n="7" type="book">
               <head>The ſeuenth Booke trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth <hi>of man.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe world hath brought foorth many things, of the which man is almoſt the leaſt. Hée hath clothed the Beaſtes, Birdes, Fiſhes and Trées, with ſkinnes, feathers, ſcales, barke, and otherwiſe. But man co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth foorth all naked ready to wéepe, and lightly before fourtie dayes, he doeth not laugh: he that ought to raigne ouer the beaſtes on the earth, is at the beginning weaker then any, he knoweth nothing without hée be taught, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to ſpeake nor to goe; and naturally doeth nothing but wéepe.</p>
               <p>Naturally the beaſtes ſéeke their liuing, flie from their enemy, ſwimme, with many other things giuen them of nature. The Lyons doe not warre betwéene themſelues, the Serpents doe not bite one another, but men ſtudie howe to deſtroy one another by warres, and diſſentions.</p>
               <p>Men neuer lightly in all points reſemble one like ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in their faces, the which commeth by the diuerſitie of the cogitations of their parentes, the which maketh their
<pb facs="tcp:10956:8"/>ſimilitudes ſo farre vnlike: and therefore the brute beaſtes that haue no ſuch varieties in their thoughtes, engender none but their like.</p>
               <p>Men there are called <hi>Arimaſpi,</hi> that haue but one eye in their forehead, which inceſſantly warre againſt the Griſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons about mettals, and they finde in the ground golde and other mettalls. Thoſe that are toward y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> end of the Weſt, drinke in dead mens ſculles.</p>
               <p>In <hi>Albania,</hi> ſome haue their eyes yellowe, that co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth to them in their youth, &amp; they ſée better by night then by day.</p>
               <p>In <hi>Affrica</hi> in ſome places there are a great multitude of Serpentes, whoſe properties they vſe for the triall of their wyues chiefly, after this ſort.</p>
               <p>If the huſbandes will haue probation of the honeſtie of their wiues: they will preſent their children before the Serpentes, which will ſtye awaye if that the children bée egitimate, but if that the Serpents remaine and feare not, then are they baſtardes.</p>
               <p>When they are bitten with Serpents, they put their ſpittle vpon the place for to heale it, ſpecially their faſting ſpittle, for the Serpe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t feareth mans ſpittle as hote water.</p>
               <p>In <hi>India</hi> there are hye men, and alſo marueilous hye beaſtes, as for a witneſſe there are Dogges as great as Aſſes, trées as hye as an Archer can ſcarce ſhoote to the top, and vnder the ſhadowe of one Figge trée, may a hundreth horſes ſtande, becauſe of the fertilitie of the lande, the tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perance of the ayre, and the aboundance of waters, there are men fiue cubites in height, the which neuer vſe to ſpit, nor are troubled with the paine of head, eyes or téeth, and are ſeldome ſicke.</p>
               <p>Others there are in the Mountaines, with heads like Dogs. In a part of <hi>India</hi> the women neuer beare children but once, whoſe children waxe ſtraight way olde.</p>
               <p>And others called <hi>Sciopedae</hi> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> haue their féete ſo broade that when they are layde, they couer them therewith from the heate of the Sunne, and they be very ſwift in running.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:10956:8"/>
               <p>Some toward the Eaſt haue no heads, but haue eyes in their ſhoulders, and others called <hi>Epithamai Pigmei,</hi> that are of one yarde hye.</p>
               <p>In the farther part of <hi>India</hi> towards the Eaſt neare to the Riuer of <hi>Gangis,</hi> there is a people clad with leaues, that liue by ſmelling, they neuer eate nor drinke in their iour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neies, they beare floures and rootes to ſmell at, and they are eaſely killed by filthy ſmelles and ſauours.</p>
               <p>There are little men called <hi>Pigmei,</hi> among which the higheſt paſſe not the height of two cubites, hauing a whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome aire and pleaſant countrey where they dwell, the which men are moleſted with Cranes, as writeth <hi>Homer,</hi> therefore it is no maruell though often times they are ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried away with thoſe Cranes.</p>
               <p>In the ſpring time the <hi>Pigmei</hi> aſſemble together moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vpon Shéepe and Goates, armed with dartes and ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes, for to deſcende downe to the ſea, and for the ſpace of thrée monethes, conſume and breake the Cranes Egges, and kil the yong ones, otherwiſe they would ſo multiplie, that thoſe little men ſhould neuer reſt in quiet.</p>
               <p>Some there are in the valleys called <hi>Pandore,</hi> that liue two hundreth yéeres, in their youth hauing white haire, in age their haires become blacke.</p>
               <p>There is a people that liueth but fourtie yéeres, whoſe wiues doe bring foorth children at the age of ſeuen yéeres.</p>
               <p>There are people that haue long hairie tailes grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. Theſe things and others hath nature made mouſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, for our examples.</p>
               <p>Among the wome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> there are diuers childings, ſome haue had ſixe children, ſome eight, and ſome nine, and ſometime children of diuers kindes, which are called <hi>Hermaphro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dites,</hi> which are both man and woman.</p>
               <p>There hath bene that haue had in their life time thirtie Children, and among the maruailes of the worlde, a childe being new borne did enter againe into his mothers wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>be, in the Citie of <hi>Saguntra.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:10956:9"/>
               <p>And it is no fable nor tale, to haue ſéene women and maydes tranſformed into men. The females are ſooner engendred then the Male, and become ſooneſt olde, the Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>males doe moue in their mothers wombe, moſt on the left ſide, and the males on the right ſide.</p>
               <p>And <hi>Plinie</hi> reciteth to haue ſéene a maide, on the night of her marriage, to be naturally tranſformed into a man, and incontinent her beard to growe, and ſhée to be married a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine to a woman.</p>
               <p>If that a woman bring foorth two children at one bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then, lightly there is ſhort life, either to the mother, or to one of her children, and if they be both Males, or Females, then are they lightly of a ſhort life.</p>
               <p>Among the women there is no certaine time prefixed of their trauailings with childe, for ſome bée deliuered in ſeuen moneths, ſome in eight, and moſt commonly in nyne moneths. Alſo ſometime at ten and eleuen moneths.</p>
               <p>Before the ſeuenth moneth the childe hath no life, the tenth day after ſhée hath conceiued. Paine in the head, a ſhadowe or miſt before the eyes, no taſte nor reliſſe in meates, and a vndigeſting ſtomacke, are ſignes of concep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. That woman that bringeth foorth a Male childe, hath better colour, and eaſier deliuerance.</p>
               <p>Miſerable is the condition of man. For the Princes by this meanes haue their originall, and are ſubiect to For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune, and hath nature as others.</p>
               <p>We reade of a <hi>Romaine</hi> Prince that died in the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning in pulling on his hoſe, an other died with the ſtinging or biting of a Grape, an other was choaked with a haire, in eating of Milke.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Scipio Affricanus</hi> was the firſt called <hi>Caeſar,</hi> for that <hi>(Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus fuit matris Vterus)</hi> his mothers wombe was opened, for him to paſſe out.</p>
               <p>Of thoſe that are cripple, lame, and conterfeite of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, commeth whole limmed and perfect children, in their members: and ſometimes of perfect and wel proportioned
<pb facs="tcp:10956:9"/>people commeth lame and vnperfect children.</p>
               <p>A woman doeth not beare children after fiftie yéeres, there are many that ceaſſe at fourtie.</p>
               <p>As touching men, we reade truely of a Prince, which at the age of foure ſcore and ſixe yéeres begate a childe.</p>
               <p>When <hi>Cato</hi> was borne, his father was foure ſcore yéeres olde.</p>
               <p>Vnto children their téeth come commonly at ſeuen mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nethes, the ſeuenth yéere they renue, for then their téeth fall, and there commeth to them others, and ſome are borne with téeth. And if that a dead bodie be burned, the téeth will neuer burne but remaine whole. Vnto ſome their téeth faile them at middle age, commonly a man hath thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie two téeth, and hée that hath more, is eſtéemed to be the longer liuer.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Zoroaſtes</hi> did laugh that day hée was borne, yea that with the very force of laughing he did reiecte the hand that was vpon his head, for the placing and faſhioning of his head, and ſetling of his braines.</p>
               <p>A man is as long from the foote to the head, as the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending or ſpreading abroade of his armes, counting from the great fingers.</p>
               <p>Men doe way more then women, the dead bodies way more then the liuing, and thoſe that are a ſléepe, way more then they that are awake.</p>
               <p>Some liue without marow in their bones, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they neuer thirſt, and for this cauſe women drinke leſſe then men: and ſuch doe neuer ſweate.</p>
               <p>It is recited of <hi>Craſſus</hi> the Senatour, that he did neuer laugh. <hi>Socrates</hi> the great clarke, was neuer ſéene mery nor ioyfull, nor angry at one time more then at an other, and therefore mens complexions are diuers.</p>
               <p>In <hi>Rome</hi> hath bene ſeene a Princeſſe called <hi>Antonia Druſi</hi> neuer to ſpitte, <hi>Pomponius</hi> neuer to belke. The ſtrength of men hath bene great, and more in one than an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other. It is read of one that with one hande did holde a
<pb facs="tcp:10956:10"/>Chariot, that thrée horſes could not make to goe for wards nor remoue.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Hercules,</hi> did carrie his great Mule on his backe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fuſius Saluius</hi> did beare two hundreth on his féete, two hundreth in his hands, and two hundreth on his ſhoulders, ſo being loden or charged with ſixe hundreth waight, went vpon a ladder.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Plinie</hi> writeth to haue ſéene one named <hi>Athanatus,</hi> to haue a iacke on his backe waying fiue hundreth waight, going to aplay with ſhooes on his féete waying fifty pound waight a piece.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Milo</hi> ſet his foote in a place, from which place, there was no man able to make him goe backe or remoue. If that he helde a ſtaffe in his hand, there was no man able to take it away or writhe it out of his fiſt.</p>
               <p>For running there hath bene many light and nimble men, that would runne a thouſand a hundreth &amp; thréeſcore furlongs a day and more.</p>
               <p>Alſo there are ſome that haue their ſight very ſinguler.</p>
               <p>We reade of a man called <hi>Strabo,</hi> of the countrey of <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cilia,</hi> that is toward the Eaſt, to recken and count the ſhips that parted from <hi>Carthage</hi> for to enter into the South ſea.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Cicero</hi> did recite that he did ſée the <hi>Iliades</hi> of <hi>Homer</hi> in verſe written, being included in a Nut ſhell, ſo ſmall were the figures.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Marmecides</hi> made a Cart, or Wagon ſo litle, that a flye did couer it. And he made a ſhip that a Bée might couer it with both her winges.</p>
               <p>For a trueth there haue bene people y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> haue heard bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tailes and fighting fiftie Leagues of, for they haue counted the time and houres of the aſſaultes. The memorie hath bene very ſinguler to ſome.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Cyrus</hi> King of <hi>Perſie,</hi> had the memorie to know and call euery one of his armie by their names.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Methridates</hi> the king did talke one day to his people, in two &amp; twentie languages without ſtutting or ſtammering.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:10956:10"/>
               <p>Others léeſe their memorie by fantaſtes, or otherwiſe haue forgotten their vnderſtanding.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Meſſalla</hi> the Orator, did forget by grieuous ſickneſſe his ſciences yea his owne name (in ſuch ſort) that hée knewe not from whence he was.</p>
               <p>Marueilous was y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> memorie of <hi>Iulius Ceſar,</hi> the which named to foure Scribes or writers at one time, and in the meane time, he read, writ, and heard, and if he had no other affaires, he would name to ſeuen. He fought <hi>52.</hi> battailes.</p>
               <p>And <hi>Marcellus 40. Ceſar</hi> in his battailes is reputed to haue ſlaine of his enemies <hi>1192.</hi> thouſand men.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Pompeus</hi> did ſpoile and take from the Pirates, and ſea robbers, againſt whome he was ſent by the <hi>Romaines 876,</hi> ſhips. Moreouer <hi>Ceſar</hi> had this conſtancie, that the letters that <hi>Scipio</hi> did ſende him for to betray <hi>Pompeus,</hi> hee caſt into the fire, without reading them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Cato</hi> was accuſed to the Senatours <hi>42.</hi> times, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies abſolued. <hi>Sicinus</hi> dictator of <hi>Rome</hi> ſuſtained ſixe ſcore battayles: he had fiue and fourtie woundes before, and not one behinde. <hi>Sergius</hi> was a worthie warrier, he deliuered <hi>Cremona</hi> from the ſiege, kept <hi>Placentia,</hi> tooke in <hi>Fraunce</hi> twelue Caſtels and Townes. He had his right hand cut off, and he made one of Iron, with the which he fought foure battailes.</p>
               <p>Pitifull things are found worthy of memorie, thorowe all partes, among the which, it commeth to my remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance, of a woman taken in <hi>Rome,</hi> for to dye for offence, and being put into ſtraight Priſon there to be famiſhed, her daughter had licence of the Iailer to goe ſée her euery day, but ſhe was ſearched for feare leaſt ſhée ſhould bring her mother foode.</p>
               <p>In the ende it was founde, that euery day ſhée did giue her mother ſucke with her breaſtes, and for to ſatiſſie her, ſhe came daily.</p>
               <p>The Senators hauing intelligence thereof, did pardon y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mother for the vertue that was in the daughter, &amp; did ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>point
<pb facs="tcp:10956:11"/>them a liuing during their liues. Marueilous are the operations of humaine creatures, among others onely of paintings, that doe reſemble the liuing ſo neere, that there reſteth nothing but the ſpeach.</p>
               <p>The king <hi>Attallus</hi> bought a table or picture of a Pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, which coſt a hundreth Markes. <hi>Caeſar</hi> bought two for eight hundreth Markes.</p>
               <p>Mans age hath bene reputed great among the ancients, which doe name Princes and Kings to haue liued eight hundreth yéeres, and a thouſand yéeres, but it is by the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rietie of yéeres, for ſo me make the Sommer a yéere, and the Winter another yéere, and others make thrée moneths a yéere, as the <hi>Arcadians,</hi> and you muſt not ſtay nor iudge things by the conſtellation of the firmament.</p>
               <p>For in one preſent houre many are borne as well ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants as maiſters, Kings and Magiſtrates, whoſe For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes are all diuers and contrarie.</p>
               <p>Many examples we haue of ſickneſſes. <hi>Publius Corne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius Rufus,</hi> in dreaming to haue loſt his ſight, became blinde and loſt his ſight. Some there are that liue but till middle age, and others that die in their youth, and nature doeth giue a man nothing better then ſhort life.</p>
               <p>To liue long the ſenſes &amp; vnderſtanding become blunt, the whole members féele dolour, the ſight, the hearing, and the going faile, the téeth alſo, and the inſtrume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts of meats: therefore age is but paine, and there is a time prefixed to liue.</p>
               <p>We reade no better example then of <hi>Zenophilus</hi> the Muſitian, that liued a hundreth and fiue yéeres without ſickneſſe. The ſignes of death, are to laugh in the furor and griefe of the maladie or ſickneſſe, to be buſie in folding or doubling the clothes of his bedde with his handes, to voyde from one in ſléeping behinde, a fearefull looke, with other things, and therefore ſéeing that by experience we ſée innumerable ſignes of death, therefore there is no certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie. Sickneſſes are diuers both to olde and yong.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:10956:11"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sirius</hi> died by the multitude of Serpentes procéeding from his body.</p>
               <p>Some haue had an Ague all their life time. <hi>Mecaenas</hi> was ſeuen yéeres in the ende of his dayes without ſléepe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Antipater</hi> liued long without ſickeneſſe, ſauing that euery yéere on that day that he was borne, he had the ague.</p>
               <p>We reade of one that liued <hi>157.</hi> yéeres, that ſlept in his age <hi>57.</hi> yéeres, and wakened as though he had ſlept but one houre. Others that haue returned a foote from their graue, when they were borne to be buried.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Pompeus</hi> cauſed a mans head to bée ſmitten off, which when it was layde againe to the body, did ſpeake an houre, both to the maiſter of the houſe, and to many others of the houſe. Death bringeth repentance. Some die for ioy: men in the hearing of ioyfull newes, of victories, and women to ſée their children.</p>
               <p>The father of <hi>Iulius Caeſar</hi> died in putting on his hoſe, and felte before no harme. Some in drinking, ſome in wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, and others in diuers maners as we daily ſée by expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience. Aunciently the vſe was among the <hi>Romaines</hi> to bury the dead, but for the often battailes of the <hi>Romaines,</hi> that had all the worlde in their ſubiection, they vſe to burne the dead.</p>
               <p>Among men <hi>Liber Pater</hi> found firſt the meanes to ſell and buy, alſo Diademes for kings, and for triumphes.</p>
               <p>The Lady <hi>Ceres</hi> founde the meanes to ſowe corne, and to grinde it, and therefore ſhe was called a Goddeſſe. For before they vſed Acornes.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Aſsirians</hi> founde firſt the meane to write letters, but the inuention hath bene ſince y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> beginning of the world.</p>
               <p>Two brethren in <hi>Athens</hi> founde firſt the meanes to make houſes and bricks.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Gellius Doxius</hi> inuented lathing and loming of walles, for before they had Caues and holes in the grounde, and they tooke example of the Swalowes, which do make their neaſtes.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:10956:12"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Cynira</hi> ſonne to <hi>Agriope,</hi> fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d out mettal of copper, braſſe, &amp; of lead, he made firſt many ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mers therewith. <hi>Danaus</hi> was the firſt in <hi>Grecia</hi> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> made welles, &amp; digged for water. <hi>Thra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> made the firſt walles &amp; towers. The <hi>Lidians</hi> found the means to dreſſe woolls. <hi>Arachneus</hi> found y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> meanes to make Linnen, &amp; Ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uas. The <hi>Egyptians</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> art of medicine. <hi>Lydius</hi> to mingle &amp; te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>per mettals together. <hi>Erichtonus</hi> found ſiluer. <hi>Cadmeus</hi> gold in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>taine of <hi>Pangy.</hi> The <hi>Ciclopia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s</hi> were the firſt workers of ſmall Iron worke. <hi>Corebus</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
                  <hi>Athenian</hi> made earthe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> pots. <hi>Theodore</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
                  <hi>Samyan</hi> made y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> firſt keyes. <hi>Palamides</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> meaſures &amp; waights. <hi>Phrigies</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> charrets &amp; wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gons. <hi>Penius</hi> the firſt trader for Marchandiſe. <hi>Ariſteus</hi> to make oyle and hony. <hi>Briges</hi> of <hi>Athens</hi> did firſt yoke Oxen to Cart and Plough. The <hi>Lacedemonians</hi> founde Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and habilime<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts for warre, Lau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces, Spears, ſwords, Bucklers, &amp;c. <hi>Cares</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Bowe &amp; Arrowes. The <hi>Phenitians</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> croſſe bowes. <hi>Belerophons</hi> firſt mou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> horſes. <hi>Palami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des</hi> in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> warre betwéene the <hi>Grekes</hi> &amp; the <hi>Troyans,</hi> found y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> order of Sta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>darts, ſignes, penuo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, ſtreamers, to giue war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning &amp; to kéepe watch. <hi>Iaſon</hi> did firſt ſayle on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Sea in long Ships, or Galleys. Before y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> time there were made little ones of wood, &amp; hydes: &amp; ſince that time ſome haue added to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> maſts, ſayles, cabels, tackelings, &amp; many other things, that we ſée by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> experience to be neceſſarie. The firſt Dials were made at <hi>Rome</hi> w<hi rend="sup">e</hi> water, according to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> courſe of the Sunne, &amp; ſince they are reduced to houſes &amp; Churches, as it is ſéen at this preſent, which was very agreable to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
                  <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maines.</hi> Finally, among al y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> knowledge y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> man hath <hi>(Plinie)</hi> thinketh this to be the chiefeſt point, for man to know him ſelfe, of what eſtate ſoeuer he be.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="book">
               <head>The eight booke treateth of beaſtes <hi>that are on the Earth.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>IN the Earth there is no beaſt greater then the Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phant, they haue knowledge to vnderſtande their Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey ſpeache, they haue obedience and vnderſtande their dueties and charges, they neuer paſſe the Sea tyll
<pb facs="tcp:10956:12"/>that their maſter or gouernour doth promiſe to bring them home againe, they knéele down for to be loden; &amp; carrie the Ladies litters in feare, prudence &amp; equitie: their téeth are of Iuorie, w<hi rend="sup">e</hi> their other bones there are made goodly woorks, they are full of clemencie, &amp; if they chaunce to finde a man ſtrayed out of his way, they knowe it, and will leade him through y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Forreſt into his way: but if they finde a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pany of men ſéeking to chaſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, then naturally they know their enemies, as other beaſts do. The Females neuer haue but one yong in their liues, they liue <hi>200.</hi> &amp; <hi>300.</hi> yéers, they loue the ſhallow &amp; cleare waters, for becauſe of their greatneſſe they can not ſwim, they eate ſtones &amp; earth, they feare cold, they will caſt to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ground w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> their fronts or foreheads, trées for to eate y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fruit. Among y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> beaſts they hate Mire, &amp; Rats, and they will not féede where as they haue runne &amp; taſted. They increaſe in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> borders of <hi>Affrica,</hi> &amp; the greateſt in <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dia,</hi> where as there are Dragons ſo puiſſant y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they ſight to the Elepha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts. They are tanied by famine, &amp; when they are tamed, they cary Caſtels on their backs in ſtead of ſaddles, wherin there may ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d ſix or eight me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; toward y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Eaſt thei make in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the moſt part of their battails, although y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they being wounded or hurt do retire. There were Elepha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts at <hi>Rome,</hi> but they were ſlaine w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſhot, for the <hi>Romains</hi> would not nouriſh the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, nor giue them to Princes. The <hi>Ethiopians</hi> make the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their veniſon, &amp; they kill the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſhooting &amp; caſting darts, which they caſt on the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſtanding in trées, where y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lephants vſe to paſſe, or els they take the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in holes or caues in the earth couered aboue, they neuer lie down, but ſléepe leaning againſt great trées, &amp; they y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> knowe their repaire, wil ſawe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> trée ſo far, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> when they come to reſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> againſt the trée, it breaketh, &amp; they fal downe, then they kil the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, (for being once down, they ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> neuer riſe again.) The blood of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lepha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts is very cold, &amp; therefore y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Drago<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s &amp; Serpents in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> countrey do aſſemble vnder their eares &amp; on their bodies, &amp; ſucke from them ſo much blood, that they therewith die.</p>
               <p>Dragons there are in <hi>Ethiopia,</hi> of ten fadoms long, and
<pb facs="tcp:10956:13"/>in <hi>India,</hi> there haue bene founde Serpentes of a hundreth foote long, and ſome will flye in the ayre to catch birdes in flying.</p>
               <p>In <hi>Affrica</hi> there are a great number of wilde horſes, and in <hi>Aſia</hi> great Aſſes like vnto Mares, but for their long eares. So writeth <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> the wiſe, which was appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by <hi>Alexander</hi> the great, to deſcribe the diuerſitie and nature of beaſtes.</p>
               <p>The Lyon is ful of nobleneſſe &amp; clemencie, the Lioneſſe for the firſt time bringeth forth fiue, the next yéere after foure, then thrée, and when ſhe bringeth but one, then ſhée ceaſſeth. The yong ones are two moneths without mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing, and ſixe moneths before they can goe, they doe ſooner aſſaile men then women, and neuer yong children, vnleſſe it be for great famine.</p>
               <p>In their age they loue and followe men, when that they can no more ſéeke their pray, and they liue till their téeth fall out. By their clemencie they demaunde nothing of thoſe that proſtrate them ſelues before them, and their yre is mitigate by prayers, as we haue ſéene by the experience of women that name them ſelues ſtrangers, and poore va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gabondes, but they are fierce to thoſe that ſtriue againſt them, their taile doeth demonſtrate their amitie and furor, as doeth the eares of horſes. When they are chaſed they neuer hide them, they knowe and purſue among others thoſe that hurt them.</p>
               <p>The female if that her yong ones are taken, cloſeth her eyes againſt thoſe that chaſe them, to the end that ſhe feare not their weapons.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Hanus</hi> was the firſt that daunted or tamed their fierce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and they are taken in holes that are made of purpoſe in the grounde. In <hi>Syria</hi> they are all blacke.</p>
               <p>The Panthers are alſo full of clemencie. Wée reade that if the Female méete a man ſtrayed or loſt in the woodes, that fléeth for feare of her, ſhée will compaſſe him mouing w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> her taile, ſhewing vnto him a ſigne of amitie &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:10956:13"/>loue, and after that hee is aſſured, ſhe will leade him into a caue or hole, where as are fallen her yong ones by miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortune, which the man pulleth out, and then ſhe tumbletly and playeth before him to giue him thankes.</p>
               <p>The Tygres are very light and nimble, therefore thoſe that ſteale their yong ones, as ſoone as the female findeth them loſt, ſhe ſmelleth their way and runneth after them, and when ſhe is ſpied of thoſe that haue their yong ones, they let one of them fall, the which ſhée taketh vp, and ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rieth it to her repayre, and in the meane time, they eſcape with the reſt, and bring them to their ſhippes.</p>
               <p>Camels they are driuen to paſture toward the Eaſt as we doe ſhéepe.</p>
               <p>Wilde Dogs haue handes and féete almoſt like men.</p>
               <p>In the North part there are marueilous ſwift beaſtes, which haue the vpper lippe ſo long, that when they will féede they goe backwarde.</p>
               <p>The Wolfe before he be ſéene, will eaſely drawe from a man his breath, they couple not with the females, but xij. dayes in the yéere. There are wilde Wolues, which in eating of their pray, if they turne once about, forget their pray, and goe againe to ſéeke another.</p>
               <p>Among the Serpents the <hi>Baſſalicke</hi> doeth infect and kil people with his looke.</p>
               <p>There are innumerable kindes of others, whereof ſome haue double heads at both endes, for to caſt venime. For the biting of an <hi>Aſpis,</hi> there is no remedy but to cutte that that he hath touched.</p>
               <p>The Cocodrils are inge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dred in <hi>Nylle,</hi> a Riuer of <hi>Egypt</hi> which haue foure féete, the ſkinne very hard, and they haue no mouing but the vpper lippe, and they make as many egges as Géeſe, and they haue ſharpe clawes for their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, in the day they remaine on the earth, and the night in the waters, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they open their throte in ſléeping, there are little birdes called <hi>Trochilos</hi> that will picke and clenſe their téeth, in the which they take great delight.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:10956:14"/>
               <p>The Stork doeth ſhew the maner how to take gliſters, for by her nature ſhe filleth her necke with water, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind with her beacke, maketh infuſion into her belly for to clenſe her.</p>
               <p>And many other beaſtes naturally knowe the herbes that for them are moſt proper.</p>
               <p>The Swallow knoweth howe to finde an herbe called <hi>Chelidonia,</hi> which ſerueth for her yong ones, when their eyes are endamaged.</p>
               <p>Of little beaſtes we finde Cities deſtroyed and people driuen away. In <hi>Spayne</hi> with Conies. In <hi>Theſſaly</hi> with Moles. In <hi>Fraunce</hi> with Frogs. In <hi>Affricke</hi> with Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſtes. In the Ile of <hi>Ciclados</hi> with Rats. In <hi>Italy</hi> with Serpentes. In <hi>Ethiopia</hi> with Scorpions.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Hyena</hi> is ſaid to be a beaſt of double nature, Male and Female, they will hearken at the Cottes of ſhepheards, &amp; learne the proper name that a man is called by, and calling him, when the man is come forth, they will ſtraightway kill him, and they will call Dogges. They are founde in <hi>Affrica,</hi> which is the cauſe of ſo many wilde Aſſes, that they ingender, the Males doe correcte the yong ones by biting, they will cut the trées along the Riuers, as with a knife, they haue tayles like to fiſhes.</p>
               <p>Déere that are oppreſſed with Dogges, if they can finde no water for their refuge, then they retire to man: the Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>male beare eight wéekes, and oftentimes two, and for to bring them foorth, they ſéeke ſecret places, not néere the hye wayes accuſtomed by men.</p>
               <p>The Hinde teacheth her yong ones to runne, to feare, and to leape, the Males that haue left the Females, haue their muſſell blacke, when they knowe them ſelues heauy, they ſéeke ſecret places, they will ſtande ſtill to heare the cry of the Dogs, they runne with the winde, to take away the ſmell of the traſe, they reioyce to heare whiſtling, and to heare a noyſe of ſinging.</p>
               <p>Moreouer the Hart is ſimple, and all things are to him
<pb facs="tcp:10956:14"/>marueilous, if that he ſee a man with a bowe, or a croſſe bowe, he looketh more on them, then on the ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, the Males haue hornes, and in the ſpring time they caſt their hornes, that day that they léeſe their hornes, they hide them ſelues as all aſtonied &amp; ſorowfull, as they that haue loſt their ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours.</p>
               <p>It is ſayde that the right horne can not bee founde, for that they hide them in the ground. At the burning of the hornes, the Serpents flye away: their hornes grow till they be thrée ſcore yéeres old, and the ſaid time paſſed, there commeth vp others like, and the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they neuer fall after that: there is no knowledge of their age, but their age is knowe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, by their téeth, they being without hornes féede in the night and when their hornes beginne to come, they will butte and runne againſt the trées, they liue a hundreth yéeres, they neuer haue the Feuer or Ague, and therefore ſome dames alwayes delight to breake their faſt with Veniſon, by the which meanes they haue liued a hundreth yéeres without hauing the Ague.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Camelion</hi> liueth not but by the ayre, and chaungeth his colour according to the thing he toucheth, ſauing white and redde, they ingender in <hi>Affrica,</hi> and in <hi>India.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Beares doe ioyne with the Females, in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of Winter, not as other foure footed beaſtes doe, for the Male and the Female lye downe embracing, and after that they doe retire in ſundry caues, and the Female doeth bring forth her yong ones within thirty dayes, and moſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>monly bringeth fiue, which haue the ſkinne white, deformed without haire, and eyes, and there appeareth but their clawes, in licking of them they are figured.</p>
               <p>There is nothing ſo little of man, as to ſée the Beare bring foorth her yong, ſhe hideth her foure monethes, and the Male fourtie dayes, they couche or lye vppon ſoft leaues, and the firſt fourtéene dayes they ſléepe ſo ſou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dly, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> you ſhall ſcarce waken them with ſtrokes, then they fatten much, and their fatte or greaſe is conuenable to many
<pb facs="tcp:10956:15"/>medicines, alſo to kéepe haire from ſheading.</p>
               <p>They being weakened for the moſt part ſtande vp, and liue with the licking of their fore féete, they warme their yong againſt their breaſts, they haue little blood about the heart, and leſſe in the body, they haue little eyes, and as fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble or weake heads as the Lyon hath ſtrong, therefore they defend their heades with their fore féete, when they fall and leape from the Rockes, or when they are bayted with Dogges. The Dogges among all other beaſtes that vnto vs are common, are moſt faithfull.</p>
               <p>We haue true hiſtories of men that haue bene defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded from théeues by their Dogges, others haue fought to reuenge their maiſters death, and conſtrained the murthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer to confeſſe the déede.</p>
               <p>Two hundreth Dogs did reſcue by force the king <hi>Gara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mantus,</hi> being taken by the hands of his enemies.</p>
               <p>Many people haue aſſembled Dogges together for the warre. We reade of Dogges that haue caſt them ſelues into the fire, when in times paſt their maiſters body haue bene burned.</p>
               <p>We reade alſo of a Dog of <hi>Nicomedes</hi> the king of <hi>By<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinia,</hi> to haue almoſt torne the Quéene in pieces, for that ſhe played familiarly with the king, the Dog thinking it had bene for harme.</p>
               <p>A Senatour of <hi>Rome,</hi> was defended by his Dogge on a night, retourning to his houſe, from the handes of thoſe, that would haue put him to death.</p>
               <p>At <hi>Rome</hi> a priſoners Dogge would neuer depart from the priſon doore, and when his maiſter was dead, he would eate nothing, and when bread was giuen him he brought it to his maiſters mouth. The ſame Dog was ſéene open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to holde vp his maiſters body being caſt into the Riuer of <hi>Tyber.</hi> They know their maiſter, and vnderſtand his voyce, aboue all other beaſtes they doe beſt knowe a mans voyce, and their names, they doe remember the wayes and iourneyes be they neuer ſo farre off, and there is noue of ſo
<pb facs="tcp:10956:15"/>long a memorie (except man.) In their chaſe they haue great diligence, ſpecially houndes.</p>
               <p>In <hi>India</hi> they tie proude Bitches to trées, and the Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gres do couer them, by the which meanes, commeth fierce and cruell Dogges.</p>
               <p>The king of <hi>Albania</hi> did giue to <hi>Alexander</hi> the great, a Dogge of marueilous highneſſe, which would take Lyons and Elephants. The Females haue whelpes thrée times a yéere lightly, and they carrie them two monethes, they are borne blinde, they can not ſee till ſeuen dayes after they be whelped: If ſhe bring but one whelpe, it ſéeth not till the ninth day, the better whelpe is that that the Bitch bringeth out firſt, or that that ſeeth laſt.</p>
               <p>Horſes are faithfull, and full of great knowledge, for they knowe their maiſters, and they that attende on them. Many are ſinguler in their doings, the Males liue till fifty yéeres, and the females leſſe, at ſixe yéeres the males grow no more, and the females but fiue yéeres. Among the beaſtes they haue leaſt fertilitie.</p>
               <p>The moſt egreſt and fierceſt Horſes, put their noſe muſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell déepeſt in the water to drinke, and haue almoſt as many diſeaſes as men. Aſſes there hath bene bought for foure hundreth Crownes.</p>
               <p>In <hi>Acaia</hi> they are much requeſted to haue Mules. They feare colde, the Males are very ſlowe in their worke, they doe beare as doe Mares, and in thirtie mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neths the yong ones are ready to helpe them ſelues. After they are horſed they muſt be conſtrained to runne, or elſe they would reiect the ſéede by making water.</p>
               <p>The females beare all their life, which is thirty yéeres, they be afrayde to wette their féete, and they neuer drinke but in ſmall and ſhallowe waters, where they are accuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to drinke drie footed, the Females doe hide themſelues when they bring foorth, in darke places, that they bee not ſéene of men, they will not paſſe the bridges when the Sunne ſhineth in the water, it is marueil that they runne
<pb facs="tcp:10956:16"/>not mad for thirſt, for he that dayly chaungeth their water or Riuer accuſtomed to drinke at, muſt conſtraine them perforce to drinke.</p>
               <p>The little Mule is ingendred of the Aſſe and of the Mare. The Mules that commeth of a Horſe and of a ſhe Aſſe, are beaſtes full of ſtrength and labour.</p>
               <p>The Aſſe that couereth the Mare bringeth forth afore her time, if ſhe before haue retained the horſe, but not elſe, the ſeuenth day the females ſhoulde bée filled, after their foale is borne, the Males fatigated of labour, doeth ſooner repleniſh the Females.</p>
               <p>Some of them are not like to their Syres, and the Mule of her nature is barren, ſauing that in <hi>Capadocia</hi> they beare, by force of drinking wine, often times y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Mules ceaſſe from caſting or ſtriking.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Athenians</hi> knowing for a trueth a Mule to haue done ſeruice foureſcore yéers, did ordaine, that in the fields none ſhould deſturbe him, neither in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> corne nor otherwiſe.</p>
               <p>The Oren liue twentie yéeres, and the Kine common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly fiftene yéeres, at fiue yéers they haue take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their ſtrength: it is ſaid that to waſh them with warme water they will fatten, the ſtrength of the Bull is at thrée yéeres: for to make them drawe, it is good to yoke them with a drawing Ore, for he will teach the other.</p>
               <p>In times paſt among the <hi>Romaines,</hi> it was eſtéemed as great offence to kill an Ore, or to ſteale one, (becauſe of their ploughes,) as it was to kill a man.</p>
               <p>The Bull requiring combat, ſheweth magnanimitie of courage and gentilitie, he turneth the head, lifteth vp the cares, remaineth on his foreféete, and maketh the duſt to die with his hinder féete.</p>
               <p>At <hi>Rome</hi> hath bene ſéene an Ore ſpeake. The Ore of <hi>Egypt</hi> hath a kyrnell called <hi>Apis</hi> vnder his tongue, and a white ſpotte on the right ſide, which groweth as the hornes of the Moone. The nature of ſhéepe is that they liue not aboue nine or tenne yéeres, the Males couple with the Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>males
<pb facs="tcp:10956:16"/>in the middeſt of May, till the middeſt of Auguſt, the Females beare a hundreth and fiftie dayes.</p>
               <p>The Ram if the right genitorie be bounde, maketh all Females, and if the left be bound in the ſeaſon, maketh all Males. If ye looke vnder the Tuppe or Rammes tongue, he doeth ingender Lambes of the colour that the vaynes are, if they be of diuers colours, he ingendreth Lambes of diuers ſortes.</p>
               <p>Alſo the mutation of waters, doeth varefie the colour of Lambes, alſo the windes. It is eſteemed not good to cut or gelde Lambes before fiue monethes, and commonly the Females bring forth not aboue foure Lambes.</p>
               <p>Goates conceiue commonly two kiddes, and ſometime foure, they beare fiue monethes as doe ſhéepe, they become barren with fatneſſe, &amp; they ingender not before the fourth yéere, they conceiue in Nouember, for to bée deliuered in March, when the trées beginne to budde: the Goate fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth cold, euery one of theſe beaſts haue not hornes, but the milke of thoſe that haue no hornes, is fatter then thoſe that haue, and thoſe that haue hornes, their age is knowen by the knots in their horns, they aſpire through the eares, and not by their noſe, and they are neuer without Feuers or Agues, becauſe of the heate of their bodies, which ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth them much ſubiect to lechery, they ſée as well by night as by day, they haue all deardes on their chinne, if one of them be taken or driuen, all the reſt will marueile thereat, if they croppe or bite a yong trée, it dieth, and if they lick an Oliue trée, it will drie away.</p>
               <p>Among the ſwine the Sowe doth farrowe two times a yéere, and ſometime they haue twentie Pigges, but they cannot nouriſh ſo many: the tenth day y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Pigges haue téeth: in once knowing the Bore they are filled, but they double it for feare not to haue retained.</p>
               <p>Some thinke that if they léeſe an eye that they wil ſoone die, otherwiſe they liue til fiftéene or twenty yéeres, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> moſt fatteſt haue leaſt milke, they willingly wallowe in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> durt
<pb facs="tcp:10956:17"/>and myre, and couch moſt on the left ſide, they fatten in ſix dayes, they know their maiſters houſe, and defend one an other, for if that one cry, all the reſt will runne thither.</p>
               <p>Among the wilde Bores, the male hath great payne to acquaint him with the Female, and ſhe hath great dolour to make her yong ones: they are borne with téeth, and are blacke.</p>
               <p>In <hi>Arabia</hi> they can not liue, neither wilde nor yet tame.</p>
               <p>Apes doe approch much to the ſenſe of man, and their kinde is, to haue no tayles, theſe kinde of beaſtes, are much affectioned to their yong ones, they kepe them or holde the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> alwayes betwéene their armes or legges, before their breaſtes, whereby many times they kill them: they haue beard on their chinne. And ſome in <hi>Ethiopia</hi> haue tailes, that can liue no where els.</p>
               <p>Of Hares there are diuers kindes, in the hie Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines, there are white ones, &amp; in Winter they liue with ſnowe. It is ſaid that a Hare is as olde as there are pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gings or voydings in her belly, they haue both kindes, and ingender one with another, and the Hare alone is meate vnto men, beaſtes and foules, and therefore hée is euer in feare, and goeth more by night then by day.</p>
               <p>Conies are of another kinde, the Males haue great de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to eate the yong ones when they are borne, but the Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>male hideth them, and they make great multiplication.</p>
               <p>Many ſortes of beaſtes there are on the earth, that doe mingle one kinde with another.</p>
               <p>Among the beaſts, <hi>Origes</hi> haue the haire long alwayes, tending towards the head, and of other beaſtes the haire tendeth towardes the tayle.</p>
               <p>Mice are ingendred on the earth. We reade that when <hi>Hanibal</hi> had beſieged a Towne, a Mouſe was ſold for two hundreth Crownes, the ſeller died for famine, &amp; the buyer did eſcape the hunger. The old Mice are nouriſhed of the yong ones, by great clemencie.</p>
               <p>In <hi>Affrica</hi> there is neither Déere, wilde Bores, Goates,
<pb facs="tcp:10956:17"/>nor Beares. In other places neither Wolues, nor Foxes. In ſome places there are no Hares, in other places no Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies. And in other places there is great diuerſitie of beaſtes, that are not in other places.</p>
               <p>The Scorpions or Serpents doe ſooner hurt ſtrangers, then the Countrey inhabitantes.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="book">
               <head>The ninth Booke treateth of Water <hi>beaſtes, and of Fiſhes.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>IN the Sea there are many great beaſtes, aſwell as on earth for the moiſture thereof, and becauſe it is more lar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger and bigger. Alſo there is many monſters and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſitie in many fiſhes, for they couple in many kindes, and there is the ſimilitude of all kinde of beaſtes on the earth, and rather more.</p>
               <p>Whales are the moſt greateſt and groſſeſt beaſtes in the Sea, there are of two hundreth yardes long. In many places there are rib bones of Whales of twenty yardes.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Alexa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der</hi> the great was afrayed to méete them, leaſt his Nauy ſhould haue periſhed. In the Sea there are Eeles thrée hundreth foote long.</p>
               <p>In the night there commeth many fiſhes out of the Sea, that wil eate the corne in the fields, &amp; after returne againe.</p>
               <p>There is in the Sea Mermaides that haue bene ſéene, and ſome that haue the ſhape of men, and their voyce like vnto mens voice, hauing the body of mans ſhape, and the lower parts ſcaled like fiſhes, with a taile.</p>
               <p>And there are Wolues, Horſes, Aſſes, Hogges &amp; other ſea beaſtes, as on the earth. If the fiſhes aſpire and reſpire as other beaſtes, there are diuers opinions.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Plinie</hi> doeth beléeue that the moſt part ſléepeth &amp; reſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth, except thoſe that haue no liuer, and in ſtéede of blood haue humor.</p>
               <p>The Dolphin is the moſt ſwifteſt fiſh in the Sea, and moſt hardeſt to be taken: euery one foloweth his like, they
<pb facs="tcp:10956:18"/>haue yong in ten monethes in Sommer, and nouriſh them as doe the Whales, the olde ones carry the yong ones, and there is alwayes a great Dolphin, that followeth the little one, they haue the tongue mouing like a Hog.</p>
               <p>Aboue the nature of other fiſhes, they loue yong childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and the ſounde of Inſtruments, they liue three hundreth yéeres, and they haue their greatneſſe at tenne yéeres, they reioyce when one calleth them <hi>Symon,</hi> and they loue hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine voyce.</p>
               <p>Many examples are both ſéene and reade of little chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, that they haue caried by Sea on their backes and brought backe againe without doing them any harme.</p>
               <p>Shell fiſhes are ſo great in ſome places, that with their ſhelles they couer their houſes.</p>
               <p>The beaſtes of the Sea haue diuers clothings, ſome are couered with leather, and with haire, as the Sea calfe, ſome onely with leather as the Dolphins, others with great thicke and harde ſhelles, other ſofter ſhelles, as Oy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, Cockles, and Muſcles, that haue no heads, others with ſharpe prickles, as the <hi>Ecchinus</hi> called the Sea Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupen, others with ſcales, as Carpes and many other fiſh, others with rough ſkinnes with the which they ſhaue fine wood and Iuory, ſome with ſoft ſkinnes, and others that haue none.</p>
               <p>The Sea calfe which is clothed with ſkinne and haire, they ioyne Male and Female together as Dogges, and they neuer haue but two at a burthen, they nouriſh their yong ones with their pappes or tettes, and are deliuered on the lande, and within twelue dayes after they bring the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to the Sea.</p>
               <p>The Sea calfe, is more grieued and more conſtrained to ſléepe then any other beaſt, and therfore their ſkinne put on a mans head, doeth prouoke him to ſléepe.</p>
               <p>Great is the diuerſitie of beaſtes, in ſome there is nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther bone nor thorne, and of many kindes there is no male.</p>
               <p>Among the fiſhes the Females are greater then the
<pb facs="tcp:10956:18"/>Males, there are ſome that haue their ſcales tending to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards their heads, cleane co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trarie to the nature of others.</p>
               <p>Some there are that goe alwayes to ſléepe vpon the drie lande.</p>
               <p>The Whale maketh her yong ones aliue without egs.</p>
               <p>Eeles liue commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly eight yéere, they will liue ſix daies without water, ſpecially when the winde is at Weſt, and leſſe with other windes.</p>
               <p>In Winter they couet déepe and cleare waters, and ſwimme in the bottome, they féede in the night, and they of all other fiſhes, ſlote not aboue water when that they are dead. In the Lake of <hi>Verone</hi> they are taken by thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſandes. Some kinde of fiſhes rendreth their yong ones aliue, others that flye by the Sea, as the Sea ſwallowe.</p>
               <p>Some make egges and couer or ſit on them, as doe the foules in the ayre, ſo doeth the Sea kite, a foule called <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerna,</hi> of the propertie of his name, ſéeketh y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> maine Seas, whoſe tongue ſhineth or gliſtereth, as may well be ſéene in a faire and calme night.</p>
               <p>The Dragon of the Sea, as ſoone as ſhe is taken and brought to land, ſhe maketh inco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinently an entery or hole in the ſande, that ſhée might be loſt. Some fiſhes haue no blood, and haue their heads in their bellies betwéene their féete, &amp; with their feete they caſt meate into their mouths.</p>
               <p>The Sea Locuſts hide them ſelues for the ſpace of fiue monethes, and ſwimme in the ſpring time, they battaile betwéene themſelues with their hornes.</p>
               <p>If they be put aliue into hote water for to ſéeth, they will be tender.</p>
               <p>The Sea Creuices liue in Rockes and ſtony places, &amp; there are very great ones.</p>
               <p>In Sommer and in the Spring they fatten, and in the full Moone, and they augment &amp; diminiſh with the Moone, they are of a long life, &amp; they haue all eight féete. The Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>males haue the firſt foote folded or double, and the Males ſingle, and they créepe as much backward as forward.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:10956:19"/>
               <p>Cockles haue two little hornes wherewith they féele the way, for they haue no eyes.</p>
               <p>The fiſhes ioyne Male and Female, ioyning their bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies, then the female ru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>neth or ſwimmeth away, touching with her muſſell the belly of the Male, and the Males eate the Females Egges, for if all the Egges ſhould profite, the Sea, Riuers, and Pondes, would be filled with fiſh, there would be ſuch an innumerable multitude.</p>
               <p>The Sea Mouſe maketh her Egges on the lande, and couereth them with earth, and thirtie dayes after doeth vncouer them, and bringeth her yong ones into the Sea.</p>
               <p>Some fiſh liue thrée ſcore yéere, as by the experience of markes put on them. Some fiſhes there are that liue on the lande, when that in Sommer, the Riuers and poudes are dried vp, and ſome will goe feede in the corne, and on the lande, tarying for the water, and ſuch is the nature of ſome, to liue on the earth with wormes.</p>
               <p>There are certaine fiſhes with ſharpe prickles on their backes, that will cut the line of fiſhers Nettes.</p>
               <p>Other fiſhes that are called Sea ſtarres, doe burne o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther fiſhes by their great heate.</p>
               <p>In the Sea there is warre among the fiſhes as among the foule in the aire, for one féedeth not with another.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="book">
               <head>The tenth Booke treateth of the <hi>Foules of the Ayre.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>IN <hi>Affrica</hi> and <hi>Ethiopia,</hi> there are birdes that are cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Struthiocameli,</hi> as hie as a man on horſebacke, which doe not forſake the earth, but runne faſter then horſes.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Phenix</hi> liueth in <hi>Arabia,</hi> I ſay not that hée is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, but neuer man ſawe him eate, he liueth ſixe hundreth yéeres, and in his age maketh a Neſt of the braunches of ſpice trées, wherein he dieth, and of his bones commeth a worme, the which afterwarde natarally becommeth a <hi>Phenix.</hi> He is as great as an Eagle, the feathers about
<pb facs="tcp:10956:19"/>his necke are of the colour of golde, the taile yellowe, and the ſurplus like to Azure.</p>
               <p>Eagles there are of ſixe kindes, ſome liue with their pray on the earth, other in the water, that fiſhe with one foote, they haue the knowledge to take Whelkes, and other ſhelled fiſh vp into the ayre, &amp; then let them fall, to breake their ſhelles, for to haue the fiſh, they cauſe their yong ones to looke vp into the Sunne beames, and caſt thoſe out of the Neaſt that will not beholde the Sunne, as baſtards: they die in their age, becauſe that their vpper bill doth growe ſo long that they can not eate, they fight againſt Déere and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Dragons, and in flying they caſt duſt that they take vp on the lande, in the eyes of Crowes &amp; other beaſtes for to blinde them.</p>
               <p>The Cuckoe reſembleth to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> colour of the wood Doue, they are killed of others of their kinde, they change their voyce, and come in the ſpring time, and doe alwayes bring vp their yong ones in other birdes neſtes, ſpecially in the neſtes of ſtock Doues, ſhe neuer lightly maketh aboue one egge, and very ſeldome two, becauſe ſhe knoweth that ſhée is hated of all other birdes. They thinke them ſelues very fayre, and diſpraiſe others, and there is no fleſh ſwéeter the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> theirs.</p>
               <p>The Kite is alwayes a reuenging foule: it ſéemeth by the remouing of their taile, that they that haue learned to guide or gouerne the ſhips by the Helme, haue learned by her. Crowes will breake or cracke nuttes, with often letting them fall in flying.</p>
               <p>The Rauens ingender by the mouth, as ſome ſuppoſe, as doe Doues: it is an euill token or ſigne when that they cry as though they were choked.</p>
               <p>The night Owles doe defend them ſelues from other foules, with their bill and clawes, becauſe they are hated they flye in the night, in winter they ſléepe two monethes, and they haue nine maner of voyces.</p>
               <p>Among the flying beaſts, ſome haue fingers and nailes,
<pb facs="tcp:10956:20"/>and other flatte &amp; brode féete, as Géeſe, Duckes, Swannes, and others liuing for the moſt part in the waters.</p>
               <p>The proud Pecocke ſpreadeth abrode his feathers, ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially againſt the Sunne, to make them ſhine, &amp; then put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth them down together: his taile ſhedeth as the leaues on trées, and commeth againe with the ſpring, when he hath no taile, he doeth hyde him ſelfe as aſhamed, at thrée yéeres his tayle beginneth to colour, and liueth xxv. yéeres, his féete are fowle, and his voyce fearefull.</p>
               <p>The Cocke knoweth the ſtarres, &amp; when the day daw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth he riſeth, and goeth to reſt when the Sunne is ſette, by his crowing hée giueth warning of the houres in the night, and waketh thoſe that goe to their labour, he is king of beaſts that are in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> houſe of his bigneſſe, &amp; fighteth with his ſpurres: if he haue the maſterie, he will ſing or crow, if hée be vanquiſhed, hée hydeth him ſelfe: hée is ſtoute in his going, and maketh the Lyon afrayde: hée beholdeth the Sunne more then any other birde: if he be kerued or gelded, he will not crowe, being kerued he will ſoone waxe fatte. The Gooſe kepeth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
                  <hi>Romains</hi> Capitol, it hath bene recited of a Gooſe that hath followed his maiſter from <hi>Swecia,</hi> to <hi>Rome:</hi> their feathers are pluckt twice a yéere, with Gooſe greaſe is made many good oyntments.</p>
               <p>Cranes they flie hie, they doe elect one whome they fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe, there are among them Sergeantes, which make the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> kéepe order in their aſſemblies, in the night they ſléepe the head vnder their wing, and one legge vnder their feathers, and ſuſtaine them ſelues with the other. Thoſe that are appointed to make watche, holde a ſtone in one of their clawes, for to waken thoſe that ſléepe, when he letteth the ſtone fall into the water.</p>
               <p>The Storkes goe their wayes in the Sommer, and none knoweth whether, nor from whence they come, aſwel as Cranes, the one commeth in Sommer, and the other in winter, they aſſemble for to take their flight, but no man euer ſawe their congregatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, for that is done in the night,
<pb facs="tcp:10956:20"/>without noyſe. They aſſemble in <hi>Aſia</hi> at a certaine day, &amp; he that is laſt come, is killed and torne in pieces, and then they take their flight. The Swannes eate Serpents, and therefore there is as great paine to kill them, as to kill a man, the yong ones doe nouriſh the olde.</p>
               <p>The Quailes come by night, and in daunger of mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners when they aproche the lande, becauſe of their great multitude. In time of raine, or of a great winde, they neuer paſſe the Seas, in winter they caſt their feathers, ſo doeth the Turtle.</p>
               <p>Swalowes liue with fleſh, they are ſo ſwift, and turne ſo ſuddainly, that no other foules can get them for to féede on, and they will féede in flying.</p>
               <p>Swallowes tarie but halfe a yéere, ſome chaunge their voyces, and their feathers mount euery yéere. The Iay lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth to ſteale Gold and Siluer. In ſome places there are no Partriges. In <hi>Rhodes</hi> there are no Eagles.</p>
               <p>At <hi>Rome</hi> in the houſe of <hi>Hercules,</hi> there entreth neither Dogge, nor flyes.</p>
               <p>And ſo it is, that in many places there is great diuerſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of birdes.</p>
               <p>Along the Sea coaſtes in ſome places there are birdes that liue with fiſh, and euery one of them maketh ſeuen Neſtes, and in euery Neſt yong ones, but their Neſtes are ſo harde, that they can ſcarce be broken, and there is no way into the Neſtes but one little hole for the Dame to come in and out, and their Neſtes are of Thornes, that are ranged one againſt another, with earth and feathers, and they are ſeldome ſéene. There are Swallowes of diuers kindes, there are ſome called Marlions y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> make their neſts ſix foote in the ground. Birdes haue marueilous great in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtrie, and knowledge in making their Neſtes, with fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, earth, and chaffe, haire, wooll, moſſe, and ſuch like.</p>
               <p>Alſo they carry water to temper it, and to fortifie it, by the which meanes their yong ones are ſure and ſafe againſt the raine, the dames doe clenſe and make cleane the neſtes
<pb facs="tcp:10956:21"/>from ordure, when their little ones are yong, and when they become great, they force them to come foorth of their neſtes for to be cleane.</p>
               <p>And in <hi>India,</hi> ſome foules ſeeke Hares ſkinnes to make their neſtes.</p>
               <p>The Partridge ſo maketh her neſt, that the wilde beaſtes can not finde them, and where ſhe layeth her Egs ſhe hatcheth not her yong, fearing that her oft frequenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſhould be knowen.</p>
               <p>The Female for the intemperancie of luſt of the Male, ſéeketh to deceiue him, becauſe if ſhe be vpon the neſt, hée will breake her Egges. The Males doe fight, for the Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>males. At the cry or ſinging of the Female, the Male run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth ſo blinded, that he will ſometimes ſtrike againſt the foulers head, he is ſo much ſubiect to imbicilitie, more then any other birde.</p>
               <p>The Female when ſhe heareth any approch her yong ones, ſhe faineth to haue her winges broken, that ſhée can not flye, and cryeth that ſhe may be heard, for to retire the people and Dogges, to the ende they finde not their neſtes, and ſhe flyeth a farre of from her little ones, and they liue, by common eſtimation, till ſixtene yéeres.</p>
               <p>The Doues are chaſte and leaue not their dwelling or remaining place, if they are not without makes, they doe ſuſpect adulterie: by this meanes they quarrell with their throte, and fight with their bill, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they flatter with their féete. The Male is as carefull toward the yong ones, as the Female: at the firſt they bring their yong of the ſalt of the earth, for to temper their appetite, and they conceiue by the bill. The Pigeons and Turtles drinke as doe hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, without often pulling their bill out of the water when they drinke: they liue about eight yéeres, but the wilde Doues liue thirtie yéeres.</p>
               <p>The Sparrow liueth not aboue a yéere, and the Female liueth ſomewhat more, becauſe of the frequentation that they haue together.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:10956:21"/>
               <p>Birdes flie in diuers kindes, ſome go, ſome leape, ſome runne, and ſome caſt their féete forewarde before they flye, as Cranes and Sorkes, and there are none but Drakes, that flye bolt vpward at the firſt leape, others aduance the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> before they flye. Some haue no féete, and haue no reſt but in their neſt.</p>
               <p>Hennes haue vnderſtanding, and when they haue laide an Egge, they cackle and make a noyſe.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Cardnelis</hi> doth thoſe things, that ſhée is comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded.</p>
               <p>The Popingay can ſpeake humaine ſpeach, they come from the <hi>Indians,</hi> they haue their head as hard as their bill, they liue moſt commonly with Acornes, and they ſpeake beſt that haue fiue clawes on their féete, they are taught ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretly where as there is no other noyſes but the teachers.</p>
               <p>Crowes haue bene ſéene ſpeake, and call noble men by their names, ſpecially one in <hi>Rome,</hi> which by that meanes was ſolemnely buried.</p>
               <p>It is eaſier to tame a Lyon, an Eliphant, or any other great beaſt or foule, then to tame a Mouſe or a Swallow.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Strabo</hi> was the firſt that did cage birdes, which before had libertie in the Sky: he taught the way to fatten Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons, with meale and milke.</p>
               <p>Among the birdes many haue foure féete, and ſome lay many egges, ſome foure, and ſome two. They ioyne toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in two maners, the Cranes, with their height. And Hennes and other Females the Cockes tread them down. Some egges, and the moſt part are white, others coloured, and others red, as the egges of Feſantes: and all kinde of egges within are of two colours, white and red.</p>
               <p>Egges of fiſhes are round, and they haue no white, ſhe Egges of feathered foules liuing on the water are rounde, and of others long: the yong ones come out of the ſhell at the round ende.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Horace</hi> ſaith that the longeſt egs haue the beſt ſauour, &amp; that Hen is beſt and moſt tendereſt, that laieth round egs,</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:10956:22"/>
               <p>Some birdes ingender at all times, as Hennes that lay euery day an egge, ſome two at a time, and ſome ſo many that therewith they dye.</p>
               <p>In ſome places Doues ingender ten times in a yéere.</p>
               <p>In <hi>Egypt</hi> the Turtle twice a yéer, and other birdes but once a yéere.</p>
               <p>As touching Egges, there is a red droppe in the mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt of the yolke, the which maketh the birdes harte, and it is the firſt formed, and of the white is formed the body, and within the Egge the head is greater then the body, and li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth with the ſurplus of the yolke: the twenty day he hath life and crieth within the Egge, and then the feathers be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginne to come.</p>
               <p>The yong one in the Egge lieth after this ſort, it hath the head vnder the right foote, and the right wing vpon the head, and they growe on their féete, contrary to the nature of other beaſtes.</p>
               <p>Ye ought not to giue a Henne aboue xxv. Egges to coue on, and thoſe Chickens that are hatched about the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the yéere, are the beſt.</p>
               <p>For to ſette Hennes to broode, take egges of ten dayes olde, for they are better then older, or more freſher, and ye ought to put odde: when the Henne hath coued foure dayes, in looking on them in the Sunne, ye ſhall knowe whether they be good or no, or in puting them in warme water, for the good Egge will ſinke to the bottome, and thoſe that are putrified and naught, will flotte and ſwimme. If the eggs are neuer ſo little craiſed y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> are ſette, they wil neuer proue.</p>
               <p>It is beſt to ſet Hennes to coue in the newe Moone, for if they are ſet in the wane of the Moone, or at the full, they will profite little. When the weather is hote, Chickens will come within one and twenty dayes, and if it be colde, not til fiue and twenty dayes. If it thunder the egs that are coued wil be loſt, &amp; alſo at the voice of the Rite or Puttock.</p>
               <p>The remedy againſt the thunder, is to put a naile in the Hennes neſt, or els of the earth of a Cart whéele.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:10956:22"/>
               <p>It hath bene recited of a Cock, which after the Hennes death hath atchieued couing, and by this meanes to ceaſſe from crowing.</p>
               <p>The Ducke meruaileth at the firſt to ſée her Duck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lins, but after moſt carefully ſhe calleth them together, and lamenteth if ſhe ſée them drowned in the water, and ſome there are that can make Chickens come in warme water, as well as if the Egge were coued.</p>
               <p>The pip commeth lightly vnto pullaine, betwéene har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueſt and the vintage: for a remedy therefore, it is good to let them hunger, and to giue them little meate, or to giue them to eate Garlike and butter.</p>
               <p>Doues they lay two egges, and if they lay thrée they will hatche but twaine, they bring foorth a Male and a Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>male, the Male firſt, and two dayes after the Female.</p>
               <p>The Male is hatched in the day time, and the Female in the night, the yong Pigeons come foorth of the ſhell twe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty dayes after they are hatched, and the Female layeth egges within fiue dayes after that ſhe hath knowen the Male. In ſommer oftentimes they haue yong ones thrice in two monethes, for if the weather be hote, they conceiue in eightene dayes, and therefore in the neſt is found many times egges and yong ones. And Pigeons conceiue at fiue moneths.</p>
               <p>The Pecock at the age of thrée yéers bringeth forth yo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g ones, the firſt yéere one, &amp; euery yéere after ſhe increaſeth, the Male breaketh the egs to haue the Female at his plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, &amp; therefore ſhe hideth her egs, and for one Male, ſhée hath fiue Females: in thirty dayes ſhée bringeth forth her yong ones. Géeſe conceiue in the water, they make their egs in the Spring: it is neceſſary to giue them nine or ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen egs to coue, at xxv. or xxx, dayes they are hatched, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly Swannes or ſuch like, coue thirty dayes, the female Crowe olone coueth, and the Male féedeth her in the neſt.</p>
               <p>The Bat hath the members and wings as feathers, ſhe bringeth two yo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g ones, the which ſhe nouriſheth with the
<pb facs="tcp:10956:23"/>milke of her breaſts.</p>
               <p>Vipers do winde one about another in conceiuing, that they ſéeme to be but one Serpent, &amp; the Female conceiueth by ſucking the Males head, which ſhée putteth into hers.</p>
               <p>Some Serpentes make her egges on the grounde, and then couereth them with earth, and the next yéere after bringeth foorth their yong ones.</p>
               <p>Men are more proner to luſt and fornication in Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then in Sommer, and women more in Sommer then in Winter.</p>
               <p>Beaſtes haue ſocietie, and knowe when the Female will haue the Male.</p>
               <p>Among the foure footed beaſtes, their ſmelling bringeth the operation of lecherie.</p>
               <p>The greater the beaſtes are, the fewer yong they bring foorth, and the longer they beare them.</p>
               <p>All beaſtes are repleniſhed with the Male at one time though they bring neuer ſo many, and the yong ones lie in the females belly the ioyntes or knées againſt the belly.</p>
               <p>But a yong Childe in the mothers Wombe hath his face betwéene his knées, and is like a Citie.</p>
               <p>Rattes and Mice doe ingender by licking one another, and it hath bene ſéen that one hath made ſix ſcore, ſo it com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth to paſſe that by this meanes there are ſo many both in the fieldes, and in mens houſes.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Salamander</hi> in touching the fire doeth quench it as if it were Iſe, and notwithſtanding that ſhe caſteth by the mouth, which is like mike, if it touch any part of a man, the haire of his ſkinne will fall away, they grow as the Eagle in the water, and among them there is neither Male nor Female, and they neuer conceiue nor make egges nor yet haue yong.</p>
               <p>Mans ſenſe is perfect, but in ſéeing, the Eagle doth ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mount him.</p>
               <p>The Vulture to ſmell, and the Mole to heare, what ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer is on the earth.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:10956:23"/>
               <p>Fiſhes doeth both ſmell and ſée, and yet haue neither eare nor hole in the head.</p>
               <p>Some fiſhes get their pray with their téeth, others with their féete, and others with ſucking and licking according to their nature.</p>
               <p>Some liue by ſucking of venime, as Serpentes, and Spiders, that haue neither blood nor heate, nor ſweate, and to them néedeth no meates.</p>
               <p>Wolues doe often times liue with earth.</p>
               <p>Beaſtes doe fatten with drinking, and therefore ſalt for them is neceſſary.</p>
               <p>Thoſe beaſtes that haue their téeth cloſe, doe lappe as Dogges in their drinking, and they that holde their téeth together doe ſowpe hume as doe Oxen and Horſes.</p>
               <p>The Beare in drinking ſéemeth to bite the water.</p>
               <p>In <hi>Affrica</hi> wilde beaſtes drinke not in the Sommer for default of water, and there are certaine beaſtes that neuer drinke, and yet they haue alwayes thirſt within the body.</p>
               <p>There is that haue a bladder full of liquor, in drinking thereof one ſhall endure long without thirſt.</p>
               <p>Birdes haue both amitie and warre amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g them ſelues as well as beaſtes on the earth.</p>
               <p>One robbeth from the other their neſtes, yong ones, Egges and meate.</p>
               <p>All beaſtes hauing hart will ſléepe, boeth on the earth and in the water.</p>
               <p>A childe newe borne (to let him ſléepe long) is to him nouriſhment, as he growes to age he ſléepeth leſſe, and yong children dreame in their ſléeping.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="book">
               <pb facs="tcp:10956:24"/>
               <head>The eleuenth Booke treateth of <hi>little Beaſtes.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>NAture hath made more meruailes, and hath giuen more ſenſe and vnderſtanding to little beaſts, wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of more greather memorie then the great. They haue no blood, but in ſtéede of blood haue humiditie and moiſture in the body, which maketh them giue both ſound and voyce, to aſpire and reſpire, they haue neither heart nor liuer, but only certaine bowels, and haue eyes &amp; other ſenteme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts and féelings, their head moueth not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the body, vnleſſe it be pulled off.</p>
               <p>Among the which, the good flies or hony Bées haue ſenſe, and labour for the publike profite, they haue among them Princes, and conductours of their counſell, and maner how to behaue them ſelues in their frequentations. In the win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter they are hidde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, for that they can not reſiſt the Snowes, windes, and froſtes, they make hony and waxe, when they goe to their worke they neuer léeſe no time.</p>
               <p>Firſt they wype or rubbe their Hiue with things that are bitter, as the Gumme of trées, and other things for to take the taſte from other beaſtes of the ſwéetneſſe of their hony: after ward they make their chambers or dwellings, then they make their yong ones without corruption, and after that they make their hony and waxe, of floures, and prouide foode for winter, otherwiſe bitter meate full of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mor ſeperated from hony.</p>
               <p>On nights in their voyage, when they are from their wonted place to reſt, they lye their belly vpward, to kéepe their wings from the dewe. The maner of their workes is to remaine ſome of them at the gate or doore of their Hyue there to kéepe watch, as the cuſtome is of a Caſtle: in the night they reſt till the morning, except thoſe that are ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed to watch, of the which one of them in the morning goeth about making a ſound or noyſe, as it were a Tru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pet,
<pb facs="tcp:10956:24"/>and then euery one departeth and flieth away if the day be faire, otherwiſe they continue in their houſe, &amp; they knowe the diſpoſition of times, the yong ones goe or flie abroade into the fieldes, &amp; the old ones remaine to make the worke, or to deuide the roomes within. Some bring the flowers to the entrie of their place, others doe diſcharge it, &amp; carieth it in, others bring water in their throte for to temper or giue moiſture to their workes, and they deuide their offices.</p>
               <p>Some do garniſh, ſome polliſhe, ſome ſucke, and others make ready ſoode of that which is brought in, for they liue together, and doe not ſeperate, to the end, that equally their foode be deuided: they make double alleyes or pathes, ſome to come in at, and ſome to goe foorth by: the moſt hony is in the higheſt roome.</p>
               <p>If there chaunce to riſe a great winde whyleſt they are in the fieldes, then they flie cloſe to the grounde along the hedges, and they take a little ſtone or earth to bée more waightier, to the ende the winde beare them not away, and lode their floures in their fore féete againſt their breaſtes.</p>
               <p>Thoſe that are appointed maiſters or ouerſéers of their houſe, will chaſtice thoſe that are negligent and ſlow.</p>
               <p>They neuer file nor make filth in their Hiue they are ſo cleane. In the night their watch being ſet, they retire into their lodging, and make a murmuring or noyſe, ſtill diminiſhing till that one maketh the laſt ſound or Tru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pet, flying in the midſt of them, and then they ceaſſe off all till the morning. Firſt they make their common houſes, and then the houſe of their king or Captaine whome they doe elect and chooſe.</p>
               <p>Among theſe good flyes, there are others more greater without ſting, which ſerue at the workes, and to chafe or warme the yong ones betwéene their féete, and they are ſtraightly corrected, and if they faile, without any remiſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
               <p>Theſe make their king a faire houſe, pinacled like a Caſtle, ſeperated from other houſes.</p>
               <p>The lodgings of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon ſort, haue ſix rowmes or cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners
<pb facs="tcp:10956:25"/>for the worke of their ſixe féete, and they make them in cloſe, darke, or raynie dayes, and at ſuch times they fill the vpper Celles with hony, and in a faire and cléere day, they goe to the fieldes.</p>
               <p>The maner how the yong ones are borne, there is great difficultie, for they neuer couer one another. There was a <hi>Romaine</hi> that made a hiue of cléere lanterne hornes for to ſée their works, &amp; it ſéemeth that they make little wormes, that become flyes, and before that they haue feathers, there is nothing that the dame deſireth more to eate, when their heads are pulled of.</p>
               <p>Their king is choſen in euery ſwarme or company, and they chooſe him that is greateſt: he is knowen, for he hath a ſpot in the forehead. If he goe or flye to the fieldes: the others followe him as his garde, and he goeth not out of the Hiue, vnleſſe that all the reſt doe followe.</p>
               <p>If he haue a wing broken or periſhed, hée goeth not out of the Hiue, he onely taketh no paines, but admoniſheth them of their worke. If by aduiſe of counſell he commeth forth, euery one putteth their paine to ſerue him, and will carry him if he be wearie. If he haue a ſting, yet he vſeth it not. When they intend to depart and leaue the hiue, certaine dayes before, they murmure and make a noyſe, and flye their way by tempeſts.</p>
               <p>Oftentimes they be at ſtrife for their bondes &amp; floures, or if one Hiue haue no foode, they will ſpoyle another, and their king doth defende them.</p>
               <p>If there wante vittailes, they kill or driue away thoſe flyes that haue no ſting. If their ſting be once broken, they are tamed or faint hearted, as a gelded body, and can profite no more, ſuch haue places a part for to retire them.</p>
               <p>They hate ſhéepe, for they can ſcarce get out of their wooll. Alſo they hate Crabbs or Creuices, and if there be any ſodden néere to their place, the ſmell of them will make them die.</p>
               <p>They haue many diſeaſes, and if any of them die, they
<pb facs="tcp:10956:25"/>bring him out of their rowmes, and caſt him out of their Hiue as making of funeralles.</p>
               <p>If their King die, they do more, for then they make ſuch dolor and ſorowe, that they doe nothing. By this and by to much taking off of their hony, they die often times.</p>
               <p>They haue ſenſe and vnderſtanding to heare, and doe reioyce, and at the ſound of a Baſan they will aſſemble.</p>
               <p>When their worke is finiſhed they flie abroade, then returne to their Hyue or houſe. Their age is ſeuen yéeres, they neuer touch any Carion, as Crowes Kites, and other flyes doe. Their hony commeth as it were a ſweate from heauen, ſpittle from the ſtarres, or liquor from the ayre, when in the ſpring time the ſaide moiſture falleth on the leaues and the Dew, and the Bées receiueth it, and carieth it into their Hyue.</p>
               <p>The hony at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> firſt is as cleare as water, it boyleth like newe wine, and purgeth, the twentie day it fatteneth, then it hardneth, and caſteth a little ſkinne like a ſcumme, there is wayes how to get the hony, for want of foode cauſeth the Bées to diſperſe and flye their wayes, or die, and to great abundance maketh them vnprofitable, for they labour no more then is neceſſary or néedefull, &amp; therefore the twelfth part is their portion that they ought to leaue them.</p>
               <p>Of hony is made many medicinable things, ſeruing to eche one. Some leaue the tenth part, and if it be not full but almoſt emptie, ye ought not to touch it.</p>
               <p>That hony that cleaueth together or thréedeth, is not good, but when incontinently it breaketh in taking of it, it is a good ſigne.</p>
               <p>Alſo the good ſmelling hony that hath a colour like gold, and ſwéete in the taſt, is a ſigne of goodneſſe. The wilde hony is not ſo good as the other.</p>
               <p>Spiders or Spinners haue within them ſuch fertilitie, that they ſpinne beginning in the middeſt, and they make thréedes very ſubtill. They make their yong ones like wormes.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:10956:26"/>
               <p>Scorpions towards the Eaſt are very venemous, and they make little wormes like Egges, of which commeth their yong ones, but in <hi>Italy</hi> they doe little harme. They byte or ſting with their tayle.</p>
               <p>Locuſtes or Graſhoppers make egges, they goe on the ground with their clawes. The <hi>Parthians</hi> do eate them.</p>
               <p>Alſo Ants make egges, of the which growe their yong ones: and as the good flyes doe congregate their workes, ſo they hide their ſoode in y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> earth, for to liue with in the win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. They haue knowledge how to deuide y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> great graine Acorne, and they drye them that are wet in the Sommer, they worke by night in the full Moone, one commeth to an other for their burthens, and it ſéemeth that in them is mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall loue in the diligence of their worke.</p>
               <p>Among other beaſts they burie one another when they are dead.</p>
               <p>The Butterflie commeth of a little worme in thrée dayes, ſhe groweth alſo of wood wherein is humiditie.</p>
               <p>There are beaſtes full of blood that die ſo ſoone as they are full, for behinde they haue no iſſue, they are ingendred vnder Oxen, and ſome time on Doggess.</p>
               <p>In <hi>Cypres</hi> there growe in the furnaces, of flies great flying flies, called <hi>Piralis</hi> or <hi>Piranſta,</hi> that die when they are out of the fire. And ſome there are called <hi>Hemorobios,</hi> that die that day that they take life. Dead flies if they be hidden or buried in aſhes, will reuine. All beaſtes haue their hornes hollow ſauing at the very end, except the Deere.</p>
               <p>Aſſes in <hi>India</hi> haue one horne. Ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> alone hath his eares vnmoueable. Hares ſléepe with their eyes ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſo do many men which the <hi>Greekes</hi> call <hi>Corybantia.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The eyes of yong Swallowes will come againe, if they be pulled out.</p>
               <p>The eyes of man principally doth ſhewe loue, furor, folly, and wiſedome.</p>
               <p>Great eyes ſignifie ſmall witte or diſcretion. The heart liueth firſt, and dieth laſt.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:10956:26"/>
               <p>A man hath eight ribbes on a ſide, the Hog ten, the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent thirtie. Among foules the Batte hath téeth and no other. Man groweth till he be xxi. yéeres olde. Blood pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerueth the life of euery perſon: that being gone: no remedy but death. They that haue the thickeſt and fatteſt blood, are the ſtrongeſt. They that haue it moſt fine and cleare, are the wiſeſt. They that haue leaſt are fearefull.</p>
               <p>The blood of an Aſſe is moſt fatteſt. The blood of a Bull will ſoone waxe hard. The blood of Déere and Goates is not thicke nor hardneth not.</p>
               <p>Man alone will chaunge his colour euen in a moment. The man that is hairie, is inclined to fleſhly luſt.</p>
               <p>If a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s haire doth not grow nor his beard, it is a ſigne that he is barre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſo is the woman y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> hath no haire growing on her body.</p>
               <p>The haire of a mans beard commeth not as the graſſe in the field that is mowed, but it proceedeth from the roote.</p>
               <p>There is no Male that hath any appearance of breaſtes but man: a woman hath two in her ſtomacke, the Cowe hath foure in her belly, Goates &amp; Shéepe two, the Sowes ten, and ſome twelue. Euery Pigge knoweth the dugge that they haue bene nouriſhed with.</p>
               <p>Whales, and Sea calues nouriſh their yong ones with milke of their breaſtes.</p>
               <p>A womans milke is vnprofitable before the ſeuen moneths. A Cowe hath no milke before ſhée hath had a calfe. The Aſſe hath milke when ſhe beginneth to beare. And to let the yo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g Aſſe take the dammes milke before two dayes, is daungerous.</p>
               <p>Certaine Dames of <hi>Rome</hi> did bathe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>-ſelues in Aſſes milke, for it maketh their ſkinne ſmooth and white.</p>
               <p>Milke of Goates is worſe to make chéeſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the milke of Kyne. The milke of beaſts hauing aboue foure breaſts, is vnprofitable to make chéeſe, and that of two breaſtes is better.</p>
               <p>The chiefeſt and beſt chéeſes are made in <hi>Italy.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:10956:27"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Zoroaſtes</hi> liued twentie yéeres with chéeſe without fée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling age.</p>
               <p>Man hath two féete of one length and meaſure, and two armes with two handes. The thombe and the little finger are of one meaſure, the other two alſo of a meaſure, &amp; that in the middeſt is longer. Euery finger hath thrée ioynts, and they ſhut or bowe inward &amp; not outwarde, the thombe hath but two that bowe in like maner.</p>
               <p>The Ape is the beaſt that moſt approcheth the faſhion of féete, hands, noſe, and eares to man, for with the foreféete he fedeth, and hath the bowels like to mans.</p>
               <p>At thrée yéeres man hath taken halfe his growth of height. He hath the knées and armes contrary in bowing, the one forwarde the other backwarde.</p>
               <p>Beaſtes that ingender their like, bowe their knées backwarde, and thoſe that make egges, forewarde. Nai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les growe vnto eche one, yea vnto dead men as well as their beardes.</p>
               <p>Birdes that haue clawes and one at the héele, ſtretche their féete toward their tayle in flying.</p>
               <p>All beaſtes haue féete in number equall. Flyes haue ſire and ſo haue Locuſtes or Graſhoppers that leape, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that their hinder féete are long.</p>
               <p>The genitors of Wolues, Fores, and Rammes are of bone. Bores haue them ioyning, and Shepe haue them hanging.</p>
               <p>The tale of fiſhes ſerueth to conduct them, &amp; ſo it doeth to other beaſtes, and all haue tayles except man and the Ape. Thoſe beaſtes haue voyce that haue lunges and ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiers. Others make but a ſounde or noyſe, and murmure inwarde.</p>
               <p>A Childe neuer rendreth voyce till he be wholly out of the mothers wombe. They that ſoneſt ſpeake lateſt goe.</p>
               <p>The voyces of men are diuers, as well as their ſimili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes and likeneſſe, and we vnderſtand them before we ſée them. The voyce of men is more grauer then the voyce of
<pb facs="tcp:10956:27"/>women. Members that growe out of time are vnprofita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, as the ſixt finger.</p>
               <p>There was one that had two eyes behind the head, but he ſawe nothing. It is a vaine thing ſaieth <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> to iudge any perſon by ſignes. Often-times commeth iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of ſhort life, that is to wit, few téeth, very long fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, colour like to lead, and other things.</p>
               <p>The contrary ſignes of long life is to crooke the ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, on one hand two ſtrikes alo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g, to haue more then xxxij. téeth, great eares.</p>
               <p>Great fore heads ſignifieth a ſtoute and manly courage, little forehead, lightneſſe, a round forehead, wrath. If the browes be ſtraight it ſignifieth imbecilitie. If they bende towards the noſe, haſtineſſe. If they bende towards the chéekes, ſignifieth a mocking perſon. If they bende wholy toward the eyes, malice and enuy. Long eyes ſignifie ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice. The greatneſſe of the eares ſignifieth a fooliſh babler. The breath of a Beare is naught, and worſe a Lions.</p>
               <p>The Serpent flieth the breath of the Elephant, and the burning of Hartes horne.</p>
               <p>The hony Bées oyle being caſt on them, dye. The <hi>Sci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thians</hi> in their warres, temper their Dartes heads in hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine blood, and in Vipers poyſon, and if they ſtrike any therewith, there is no remedy but death.</p>
               <p>The beſt foode for man is to eate but of one meate at one time or meale, the accumulating of ſauours is peſtiferous, and Wine maketh a ſmelling or ſtinking breath, if it bée not tempered. With great difficultie ſhall a man digeſt that which is taken gréedely, exceſſiuely, or haſtily.</p>
               <p>There is more paine in the ſtomacke to digeſt in Som<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, then in Winter, and in age more then in youth.</p>
               <p>The vomitings that are made after exceſſe, maketh the body colde, are hurtfull to the eyes and téeth.</p>
               <p>A mans body groweth and wareth groſſe, to vſe ſwéete things, fatte meates, and good drinkes. A man may eaſely liue ſeuen dayes without drinke.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:10956:28"/>
               <p>Butter aſſwageth hunger and thirſt: neuertheleſſe things exceſſiuely taken are hurtfull, &amp; therefore it is good to deminiſh that away which hurteth.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="book">
               <head>The twelfth Booke treateth of <hi>ſweete ſmelling Trees.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TRées haue life which they take of the earth. There are many ſtraunge trées in diuers countreies, which vnto ſome are vnknowen.</p>
               <p>In ſome places they water fine trées at the foote with wine, the which profiteth much the rootes.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Parthians</hi> which haue trées bearing wooll, of the which is made fine Cotto<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> cloth, as it is ſaid, haue a trée bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring Apples, but y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fruit is not to bée eaten, but they haue a meruailous ſmell, ſo haue the barkes, the which being in your Cheſt among your apparell, caſteth a ſwéete ſauour or ſmell: and this trée hath alwayes fruite, ſome growing, ſome dying, and ſome ready to gather, and the graftes of this trée will take in no other countrey.</p>
               <p>In <hi>India</hi> there is both wood &amp; trées that will not burne in the fire. There hath alſo béene ſéene a Figge trée of a great height, the braunches of the ſame trée to ſpreade ſixty paces, and it hath leaues ſo brode, that the Sunne beames can not by any meanes enter betwéene, and therefore the fruite of this trée can not dye, but the ſhadowe of the ſame is very delectable.</p>
               <p>There is alſo in the <hi>Indias,</hi> Apple trées which haue the leaues thrée cubites long, and two brode, bearing ſuch great fruit, that foure men can ſcarce eate one Apple. The trées name is <hi>Pala,</hi> the Apples name <hi>Aripa.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Pepper groweth on little trées as doeth Ienuper.</p>
               <p>In the <hi>Indias</hi> it is ſometimes mingled with Ienuper berries of that Countrey, which haue ſome ſtrength, but no ſuch taſte: it groweth almoſt white, but for to laſt it is dryed in the ſmoke, which cauſeth it to be blacke, and with
<pb facs="tcp:10956:28"/>the ſhrubbes of the ſame trée dryed in the Sunne, is made long Pepper.</p>
               <p>There are other trées which in the morning after the dewe, rendereth a certaine kinde of hony.</p>
               <p>In <hi>Arabia</hi> there are trées which neuer caſt their leaues. Others that haue their floures, that beginneth in the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning at the Sunne riſing to open, and at hye noone they are opened, &amp; after noone they beginne to cloſe, and ſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine all night till the morning, and the Payſauntes of that countrey ſay that the trée ſleepeth.</p>
               <p>There is the trée of <hi>Nardas,</hi> the which caſteth a meruai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous ſweete ſmell or odour.</p>
               <p>And in <hi>Arabia</hi> of Trées growe Frankencenſe, and Myrre. Frankenſence groweth in a Forreſt of <hi>Arabia,</hi> in a fruitfull grounde, full of Fountaines pertaining to diuers perſons.</p>
               <p>It is a hanging matter among them to ſteale any thing.</p>
               <p>The men do purifie them-ſelues, and abſtaine from wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men for a certaine ſpace, to take or gather the Franken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, otherwiſe they can not profite.</p>
               <p>On this ſide the Sea it is mingled with a kinde of Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen which is like, but the difference is knowen by the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour, by the breaking, and by the fire, for Frankenſence will ſooner burne, and is ſooner broken with your téeth.</p>
               <p>Alſo there is in thoſe woodes of <hi>Arabia,</hi> trees bearing Myrre, and the Maſticke.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Sabians</hi> burne no other wood, wherefore they are weary of their ſmell.</p>
               <p>In the Sea of <hi>Arabia</hi> groweth the <hi>Margets</hi> and other precious ſtones.</p>
               <p>Synamon is the barke of a little trée, which groweth in great quantitie in baſe <hi>Ethiopia,</hi> in ful places among the buſhes, the beſt is that of the higheſt branches, the worſt is that that is neareſt to the roote. When there is any dewe in the Sommer it is gathered by great difficultie.</p>
               <p>The trée hath no ſmell whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it is gréene, &amp; it is gathered
<pb facs="tcp:10956:29"/>from the Sunne riſing, to the Sunne ſetting.</p>
               <p>The ſhippes remaine ſixe monethes for their: fraught. That that is caried into this countrey of <hi>Ethiopia</hi> to ſell them, is Glaſſes, veſſels of Copper, and Braſſe, Wollen cloth, and Linnen.</p>
               <p>The worſt barke or pelle, is that that is ſoft and white.</p>
               <p>Baulme groweth onely in the prouince of <hi>Iuda,</hi> in two Gardens of the Kings, the one co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>taining about ten Akers, the other leſſe, and it commeth of little trees not foure foote long, growing after the maner of a Vine, it reſembleth and is neare to the taſte of Wine, red in colour and fatte, the fruite is cutte with a knife of glaſſe, ſtone, or bone, for the braunche dieth to be cut with Iron, and it is cutte to take away the ſuperfluities, then in the ſeaſon the barke is onely cutte, and then commeth out the ſweate by ſmall droppes. This experience is true, that if any of it be ſpilt vpon any apparell, it will neuer ſtaine.</p>
               <p>There is daunger in Wormes, for they will marre the trée. <hi>Alexander</hi> the great in a Sommers day filled a little Viall of one trée.</p>
               <p>Ginger groweth in the earth, and is rootes.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="book">
               <head>The thirteenth Booke treateth <hi>of ſtraunge trees.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe ſwéete oyntments, perfumes, and ſmellings, are made of theſe trées. Some for the pleaſure of others buye them deare, for they that carry them, haue not the ſmell &amp; pleaſure, but it is for the ſmell of others, which is great vanitie.</p>
               <p>Palmes are in diuers kindes, and there are none fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full but toward the Eaſt, for they make wines: and as in trées and leaues there are Male and Female, ſo there is alſo in theſe.</p>
               <p>The Male buddeth within the roote, and the Female outwarde.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:10956:29"/>
               <p>They beare euery yéere Apples, and when the trée is cut the roote caſteth againe.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Cedar</hi> groweth in <hi>Siria,</hi> of which commeth the ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueraigne roote. That that flouriſheth beareth no fruite, &amp; that that fructifieth beareth no floore, and the wood laſteth perpetually.</p>
               <p>The Figge trées in <hi>Egypt</hi> are like to Mulbery trées, the fruite commeth foure times a yéere, againſt the woode and not againſt the braunches.</p>
               <p>There are many vnknowen trées, ſpecially thoſe that haue the good Gum. There are made Cordes or Ropes of this trée.</p>
               <p>At <hi>Rome</hi> haue béene founde bookes of Philoſophie in a Sepulchre betwéene two ſtones couered with Cedar wood that had laine there fiue hundreth thirtie fiue yéeres with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out harme, for the Cedar neuer rotteth, and there is no wood ſo good to make workes.</p>
               <p>There are Cedar trées ſo hie, that ye can not ſée the toppes, and ſo great that there was preſented to <hi>Tiberius Caeſar,</hi> a table that was foure foote large, &amp; ſixty foote long.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Lotten</hi> or <hi>Celtis</hi> is a trée in <hi>Affrica,</hi> the fruite of which is ſo ſwéete that it healeth all paines in the belly, and out of that fruite being bruſed or preſt, commeth wine that will not continue aboue ten dayes.</p>
               <p>Pomegranets there are of diuers kindes, ſwéete, ſower, and winiſh. The pell of the ſower ones, are good and beſt to tanne ſkinnes, and the floures are good for Dyars.</p>
               <p>The Thorn that is called Royal, groweth in one day, and kepeth wyne from being naught.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Citiſus</hi> is a ſingular trée, the wood is good to all beaſtes, as well Shéepe as others. If <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e ſodden in water, it ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreth to Nources that drinke it, plenty of milke, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth the children more ſure and more greater, and maketh Hennes to lay egges. Vpon the floure of this trée a flye will neuer ſitte.</p>
               <p>Many other ſtraunge trées there are in the Sea, that
<pb facs="tcp:10956:30"/>will breake like glaſſe, &amp; others that are as hard as ſtones, and many other trées that are in the Ilandes of the Sea, which we haue not here, and which vnto vs are alſo vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowen.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="book">
               <head>
                  <hi>The foureteenth Booke treateth</hi> of Trees and fruitfull Plantes.</head>
               <p>IN times paſt men were wonte to haue many pleaſant trées, of the which nowe there is no mention, for euery one ſtudieth couetouſneſſe.</p>
               <p>The Wine groweth of wilde plantes, and among all other plantes it is the principalleſt fruite, and there are many kindes, and euery yéere it muſt be cut, or elſe other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe it would compaſſe a whole Towne.</p>
               <p>Wine is the blood of the Earth, it being taken within a mans body is hote, and without it is colde, it is bothe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable and profitable to a man, if it be taken meaſurably, otherwiſe it is very hurtfull.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Alexander</hi> the great did vanquiſhe the whole worlde, and yet could not ſo well kéepe him ſelfe, but was ouercome with the force of Wine.</p>
               <p>Wines is not permitted to the wiues of <hi>Rome.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>We reade that King <hi>Romulus</hi> did pardon and forgiue a Senatour of <hi>Rome</hi> called <hi>Ignatius Mecenius,</hi> which had kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led his wife with a Clubbe, for that ſhe was founde drin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king wine out of a tunne.</p>
               <p>And therefore <hi>Cato</hi> did ordaine that women and may<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens ſhould be kiſſed of their parents and kinſfolke, to the ende they ſhould knowe whether they did ſmell of Wine or no.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Marcus Varo</hi> writeth of a Conſull which neuer made banquet, nor had at his table more at one time then at an other, for feare of to much drinking.</p>
               <p>In times paſt at <hi>Rome</hi> the price was ſet on wine, to the ende that little ſhould be drunke, but ſince <hi>Caeſar</hi> made
<pb facs="tcp:10956:30"/>great banquettes, which gaue occaſion to make prouiſion at <hi>Rome</hi> for all kinde of wines. Wine alone ſerueth to make medicines.</p>
               <p>There is wine made of Peares, Apples, and of other trées, which they vſe toward the Eaſt.</p>
               <p>Some make Wine of hearbes, of water and hony ſod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, which in <hi>Wales</hi> is called <hi>Metheglyn,</hi> that will laſte fiue yéeres, or with Hony and Vineger, which is called <hi>Oximell.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The ſmall wines ought to touch the ground for to bee the better kept, but not the good. The flower of white wine is good, and that of red is naught. By drunkenneſſe men reueale their ſecrets, and make debates.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="book">
               <head>
                  <hi>The fifteenth Booke treateth</hi> of Trees bearing fruite.</head>
               <p>THe Oliue trée groweth not neare the Sea, nor in places to hote nor to colde: they muſt bée cut like Vines. The Oliue oyle is of a better ſauour when the Oliues beginne to ripe, but there is not ſo much when they beginne to be black, but that is the time to take them, and of their ripeneſſe. There is more paine to make Oyle then wine.</p>
               <p>The Oliue hath ſtone, oyle and fleſh, the gréene are bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, by drying they become leſſe though y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the heate is cauſe of oyle. The liquor of the Oliue is the oyle, but it laſteth not as doth wine, for it is beſt the firſt yéere.</p>
               <p>Some there are that tary til the Oliues fall from trées, for it hurteth the trées againe the yéere following, to bée cut, broken, or ſmitten.</p>
               <p>Oliues before they are rype will be kept with ſalte, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that they haue bene in hote water.</p>
               <p>If the Oliue be not cleane, it is waſhed and dried, thrée or foure dayes and ſeaſoned with ſalt.</p>
               <p>There is Oyle made of many things, of Nuttes, of
<pb facs="tcp:10956:31"/>Acornes, of ſmall graines, of ſwéete ſmelling trées, of Gumme that ſerueth for medecines, of Almonds, Cheſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuttes, and diuers other things, according to the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treies. Apples and Peares ought to be kept in a drie and colde place, and for them the North winde is good and no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther wyndes, when the weather is faire, they ſhould be put on hay, ſeperated one from another for to take the ayre, and they ought to be gathered before the full Moone.</p>
               <p>Nuttes make a ſound or ratling in falling, when they are rype, and among other fruites they are parted in foure within, with a little ſkinne betwéene both. They will kéepe gréene, being put in earthen pottes, in the earth, and with them is made good Oyles.</p>
               <p>Cheſtnuttes, are a kinde of maſte, and it is meruaile that nature hath ſo cloſed them in ſhelles.</p>
               <p>Mulberies ſtayne a bodies fingers, and they are of thrée colours, at the firſt they are white, after that become redde, and when they are ripe then they are blacke.</p>
               <p>Cheries will kéepe dried with the Sunne, as Oliues. There are many releſſings in fruites, as ſwéete, wateriſh, ſower, bitter, gréene, ſalt, brackiſh, fatte, and diuers others, amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g the which there are that haue many taſtes together.</p>
               <p>The Wynes are ſwéete and ſower, pricking. Milke is ſwéete and fatte, but there are thrée principall Elementes, without ſauour and without ſmell, as water, fire, and the ayre. The Laurell is dedicated to triumphes, and Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours beare thereof on their heads, principally becauſe it kéepeth the perſons from thunder.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="book">
               <head>The ſixtenth Booke treateth <hi>of wylde trees.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe Acornes commeth of Oke trées of diuers ſortes, for ſome there are better then others, and in time of famine y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> good Acornes dried may be grinded to make bread. Acornes be moſt ſwéeteſt when that they are
<pb facs="tcp:10956:31"/>newe, and roaſted in the imbers.</p>
               <p>The Oke is beſte for to builde withall, either houſes or ſhippes, becauſe it will longeſt laſt.</p>
               <p>If an Oke trée be ſmitten with the thunder, it beareth fewe Acornes or none, and is ſo bitter, that no beaſte will eate thereof but Hogges, and when they are very hungry.</p>
               <p>The Béeche trée, beareth a kinde of maſte the whiche reioyceth the Hogges being fedde with them, their fleſh is ſoone ſodden, and very profitable for the ſtomacke.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Taxus</hi> is a trée like vnto a Pyne trée.</p>
               <p>In <hi>Arcadia</hi> it is ſo venemous that no beaſt dare ſléepe vnder the ſhadowe of it, nor eate thereof.</p>
               <p>The Cuppes that are made of this wood, to put Wine in, are venemous.</p>
               <p>It is ſaid that the venime of this wood ceaſſeth, when there is nayled therein a nayle of braſſe.</p>
               <p>An Eſhe trée, the leaues thereof is mortiferous to Mares, but it hurteth not the beaſtes that ſhadowe vnder it, to drinke the liquor of it, is good againſt the biting of Serpents, for neuer Serpent reſteth vnder the ſhadowe thereof, and he that will compaſſe a Serpent about a fire with the leaues of this trée, the Serpent will rather take the fire then eſcape through thoſe leaues.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Tilia</hi> of ſome called the Teybe, hath Male and Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>male, for the Female alone beareth floures and ſéede. The iuyce of the barke and leaues is ſwéete, but no beaſt will eate of the fruite, betwéene the barke and the wood there are many little thinne pelles or ſkinnes, with the which are made Ropes.</p>
               <p>The Maple if it were ſo great and ſo high as the Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dar, ſhould be preferred becauſe of his properneſſe.</p>
               <p>With this trée is made Tables being of a blackiſhe colour.</p>
               <p>The Boxe trée ſpreadeth very large and thicke, and is very proper becauſe of his ſhadow.</p>
               <p>There are certaine wilde trées, that neuer léeſe their
<pb facs="tcp:10956:32"/>leafe, as the Cedar, the Ieniper, the Holly trée, and others.</p>
               <p>The Ieniper for his leafe hath a ſharp pricke or thorne.</p>
               <p>There are certaine places in <hi>Egypt</hi> whereas ſome trées will not growe.</p>
               <p>Other trées there are that leaue their leaues ſooner then the reſte, and the difference thereof commeth, for that their fruite is ſooner rype then others: but Almond trées, the Eſſhe, and others, haue their fruite with the firſt, and caſt their leaues with the laſte.</p>
               <p>The Mulberie trée bringeth her fruite late, and falleth her leaues with the firſt.</p>
               <p>The trées after the maner of beaſtes doe conceiue in Ianuarie with the winde, ſome ſooner then others, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter a ſtraight winde, beginneth the floures to appeare, and nouriſh the fruite.</p>
               <p>Vines in ſome places beareth twice a yéere. The rootes are diuers according to the diuerſitie of trées.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Eſculus</hi> as writeth <hi>Virgil</hi> is a trée, that hath ſuch pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>funditie or déepeneſſe in the earth, as it hath aboue the ground in height.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Ciper</hi> trée is flowe in growing without the ground be fat and fertile, then it ſpreadeth very large and long. And thus to conclude, I finiſh this abſtract, till further occaſion ſhall ſerue, geuing God moſte hartie thankes for theſe his benefites and giftes geuen for the vſe of mankinde. To whome be all honour and praiſe for euer and euer A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:10956:32"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
